<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the answerer of the letter sent to the author of a paper called The doctrine of passive obedience and jure divino disproved</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57021</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13133636</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97880</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870892</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12712</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13133636</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 749:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the answerer of the letter sent to the author of a paper called The doctrine of passive obedience and jure divino disproved</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 65, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Hickes, George, 1642-1715. --  Doctrine of passive obedience and jure divino disproved.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO THE ANSWERER OF THE LETTER Sent to the AUTHOR of a PAPER, CALLED The Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Jure Divino</hi> disproved▪</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Math. xxvi 52.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Angliae</hi> res compositas velim, illaeso Regis <hi>veteri jure.</hi> Grot. ad frat. Gul. Grot. <bibl>Epist. 635.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Gaudeo ad probandam <hi>veram, veteremque Christianorum sententiam de non opponendâ Regibus vi,</hi> Aberdonensibus <hi>probatam; neque inutiles ad id fuisse labores nostros:</hi>
               <bibl>Idem. ad Sams. Johnsonum Epist. 1118.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:2"/>
            <head>Advertisement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe Printer having mistaken in Printing the <hi>Columns,</hi> p. 23, 24, 25, 26. 'tis thought convenient to advertise the Reader, that all which follows after <hi>Column</hi>—p. 21. l. 33. shou'd be struck out, and instead thereof these words shou'd be added—<hi>The Chief Texts which you quote in another; to which I shall also annex some Observations upon our Author's Expositions, as likewise some Remarks upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Late Author; and Lastly I stall give the true and plain meaning of these Texts (as the ancient and most Orthodox Expositours understand them.</hi> The Reader also is desired, to take notice that the Titles—<hi>The Author's Comment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the Texts of Scripture</hi> ought only to be set upon the Two first <hi>Columns</hi> p. 22. and the latter of them upon p. 23. on the right-hand-<hi>Column</hi> only. And p. 57. lin. 31. after—<hi>Election it self</hi>—these words shou'd be added—<hi>(provided the Constitution of the Kingdom be Elective)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 5. l. 27. betwixt <hi>have</hi> and <hi>inheritance</hi> add <hi>we.</hi> p. 7. l. 24. for <hi>Rehoboam</hi> r. <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam.</hi> p. 7. l. ult. for to r. against. p. 24. <hi>Column</hi> second l. 24. for <hi>he</hi> r. <hi>the.</hi> p. 48. l. 11. dele <hi>that.</hi> p. 57. l. 31. dele <hi>not.</hi> p. 59. l. 21. <hi>for yet is</hi> r. <hi>yet it is.</hi> p. 59. l. 30. after <hi>sworn</hi> add <hi>to maintain.</hi> There are other faults, which the ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will easily excuse and correct.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97880:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO THE ANSWERER OF THE LETTER Sent to the AUTHOR of a PAPER, CALLED The Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Jure Divino</hi> disproved.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Preface to the Objections sent against your half sheet, your pleas'd to call an <hi>unnecessary Prologue,</hi> which therefore you have thought fit wholly to omit. I am willing to give you as little trouble as may be, and shall not spend time in proving either the necessity or pertinency of it. Whether it was properly accommodated to your Person you know best, and with your Conscience I leave it. However if I was mistaken in my suspicions concerning you, you resolve, it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97880:3"/> seems, to be even with me; when, without mincing the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you call me <hi>notorious hypocrite:</hi> And that for no other Reason, but for <hi>Preaching up Passive Obedience to others,</hi> and yet at the same time, assuring you, <hi>that I am and shall be, as averse from having my throat cut as you are.</hi> p. 3, 6. of your Answer.</p>
            <p>For, Pray Sir, consider again, cannot I be for the Passive Doctrine, but I must be <hi>willing to have my throat cut?</hi> And if I be not willing to <hi>have my throat cut,</hi> must <hi>I need be for resisting any Man or Men whatsoever, who shall endeavour to take away my life contrary to Law?</hi> What connexion is there betwixt these things? Or does there need an Oedipus to reconcile these <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties</hi> (as you call them)? May I not love my life so well, as to be <hi>unwilling to have my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hroat cut?</hi> And yet may I not at the same time, have such a re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard to my Duty, as to be willing to part with my life rather then loose it Eternally, by ranking my self amongst the number of those, who by resistance, <hi>shall receive to themselves damnation?</hi> Upon second thoughts, it's probable, you may think your self too blame for passing such a rash censure upon me. However, I'm well assured, that no sober Man and good Christian, will judge me worthy of the Character of <hi>notorious hypocrite,</hi> meerly because I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to preserve my Life, as a Man endued with natural Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, when yet I am ready to lay it down, rather then save it by such practises, as I judge repugnant to my Duty as a Christian, oblig'd by the Laws of Christianity.</p>
            <p>In Truth, Sir, to deal plainly with you, your Reasonings in the Judgment of some of your Friends as well as my self, have so little weight and moment in them, that I am likely to make but very small Improvement of my time, by under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to examin and refute them. Abating some of your hard Words (such as <hi>inhuman and damnable Principles</hi> p. 37.) you bring nothing that would affrighten a well Educated School Boy (who, out of his <hi>Catechism,</hi> has been instructed in his Duty to God and the King) from undertaking you. I confess, by your half sheet, I guess'd that I had <hi>ingaged with a</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97880:3"/> Master in the Cause; and was afraid that your streng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of Reason, and dextrous Management might have caused me to have repented of my rashness, and have at least exposed me as an incompetent Defendor of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> tho' in it self, it be never so capable of being defended.</p>
            <p>But I perceive, it is not always true, that second thoughts are the best and wisest; and that some Persons, to the end that their Readers may believe more then they can prove, boldly venture to promise more then they can perform. And whether or no you have made use of this Artifice (so common with all great undertakers) I leave it to any one to determin; who will take the pains to compare the several Propositions of your Title-page, with what you have said in the Body of your Book to prove them. He must be one of the <hi>meanest capacity</hi> indeed, who can perswade himself that you have made good your Title-page Propositions; unless it be to <hi>the meanest capacity</hi> in this sense.</p>
            <p>You have (you say) set down my Answer <hi>Verbatim,</hi> that the <hi>Readers may better judge of the ridiculousness thereof.</hi> What the Readers will judge of my Answer, I know not; however I am oblig'd to you for your kindness. Pardon me, Sir, if in requital I do not set down your Reply <hi>Verbatim;</hi> for this would be to <hi>Ridicule</hi> the Reader as well as to render the Reply it self <hi>ridiculous.</hi> I shall therefore only desire the Reader (of what perswasion soever, if intelligent) first to consider what you promise in the Title-page, and then examin whether you have substantially proved any one (much less every one) of those specious Propositions, with which you flatter the People? And if none of those nine rare things, which you promise to shew, shall appear to him after he has perused all your Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs, he'l be apt, I believe, to judge you <hi>ridiculous,</hi> or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worse. They must either want wit or honesty, who propose mighty matters, when they perform little, or nothing at all. Yet such Quacks there are, and always will be in the World; and whether you be not sufficiently qualify'd to set up for one of them, I shall leave those to judge, who have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97880:4"/> so much time to throw away, as to take a view of your won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful curiosities.</p>
            <p>But 'tis time to come to particulars. And here, because we seem to be agreed about the number of Breaks or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, in the first Paper, I shall observe the same Method in my Remarks upon your Reply, which you have; in your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations upon my short Return, to your <hi>couragious Challenge to all the poor Passive Obedience and Jure Divino Men in all</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>nay in the whole World.</hi> And I intreat no other favour of those, who shall think it worth their while to judge betwixt us, but that they will first read over every one of the Breaks or Sentences in the first Paper (which gave occasion to this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute) and then consider my Answer thereunto; before they proceed to <hi>the Author's</hi> Animadversions thereupon; which when they have impartially examin'd, I desire, in the last place, that they will read over this Rejoynder; and then, without Favour or Affection, judge whether of us two hath Right on his side; and hath done most Justice to the Principles of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Religion, the Laws and Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 1.) To begin. In your first Paper, your first Proposition is, that <hi>God by no Word Binds any People to this or that Form of Government, till they, by their own Act, Bind themselves.</hi> To this I Answered, —<hi>That Monarchy is the Government which God hath chosen above all others; and that the People, were always obliged to accept of that Form of Government which God had chosen for them, before they did actually Bind themselves. SEE HIM</hi> (said <hi>Samuel</hi> to all the People) <hi>WHOM THE LORD</hi> (not you) <hi>HATH CHOSEN.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> x. 24. Now what is your Reply? Why you quote a great many Texts of Scripture, and when you have done, make your own Remarks upon them, and then think you have effectually answer'd me. For example, because the Text says.—<hi>He told the People the manner of the Kingdom, and wrote it in a Book, and laid it up before the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. x. 25. you argue thus.—<hi>Surely no Man will say, but that this Law was a Rule for the King to go by as well as the People. And then, where</hi> (you ask) <hi>was his Absolute Authority?</hi> In which Argument you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97880:4"/> insinuate, as if I denyed that the Law, or <hi>Manner of the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gdom</hi> was a Law to the King as well as the People. Which I am so far from maintaining, that on the contrary, I do say, that the King as well as his People is obliged in Conscience and in the sight of God to observe the Law, as far as it concerns him. <hi>Saul</hi> when he broke the Law, which God had made the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his Power, was in the Court of Heaven no more excusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than one of his meanest Subjects. Yet his Subjects had no Warrant to call him to an account for what he had done. So that his Authority, in this respect, was not at all diminished by the Law or <hi>Manner of the King.</hi> And thus you have an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to your Question, <hi>where then was his Absolute Authority?</hi> And indeed you do unluckily Appeal to this Law, or <hi>Manner of the Kingdom, which</hi> Samuel <hi>wrote in a Book, &amp;c.</hi> For the Right or Prerogative of the King is therein so described, that it gives him an <hi>Absolute Authority indeed,</hi> over the People, whilst it leaves to them little else but the Obligation and Duty of Obedience. Such a Law or <hi>Manner of the King</hi> as this was, you would I believe, be very loath to have entered into our Law-Books, and inserted into the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because the People did solemnly own, recognise, and (as you express it) <hi>confirm</hi> their Kings, this (say you with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular respect to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Case) <hi>makes not a little for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Right in electing their Kings.</hi> In truth this makes just nothing at all for the People's Right in electing their Kings. For how, I beseech you, doth it appear, that the People, have any Right to <hi>elect,</hi> when they are only to <hi>approve</hi> and <hi>receive</hi> him, whom God before hath chosen for them; as in the Examples of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> to which you refer; i <hi>Sam.</hi> xi. 14, 15. i <hi>Chron.</hi> xxix. 22? As for what I said concerning <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> you grant that <hi>he was elected by the People;</hi> but withal (you say) that he was <hi>King by the appointment of Almighty God.</hi> And so indeed he was, as War, Pestilence and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine are by the <hi>appointment of Almighty God</hi> but no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; notwithstanding that Text, which you cite for this purpose very fallaciously. But so it often happens, that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97880:5"/> who accuse others wrongfully, are themselves suffer'd to fall into that Guilt which they charge upon their innocent Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <q>You ask me with what face I can wrest the Scriptures thus, in saying that the People's chusing <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> is more then once called a Sin (Rebellion) when both these Texts, which you quote, relates to the foregoing Verses, wherein 'tis said, that <hi>King</hi> Rehoboam <hi>sent</hi> Adoram, <hi>that was over the Tribute; and all</hi> Israel <hi>stoned him with Stones, that he dyed?</hi> which (Act of the People) was (you say) Rebellion, because it was resisting the lawful Authority; besides <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> is not mentioned as King, till after this Act was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</q> This is the charge (with the Reasons thereof) which you exhibit against me. I shall now clear my self, and then shew, that the Fault you accuse me of, you have really made your own by misapplication of Scripture to your present purpose, either through Ignorance, or (which is worse) evil Design.</p>
            <p>As to the first I say again, that those Places, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> xii. 19. and ii <hi>Chron.</hi> x. 19. do relate to the Rebellion of the Ten Tribes in falling off from <hi>Rehoboam</hi> their lawful King, to <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Usurper. For, as soon as they had heard <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s Answer, which was according to the Counsel of the young Men, <hi>v.</hi> 14. they presently began to be Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, gave the Signal of War, and were resolv'd to have a King of their own making, and to cast him off, who was the rightful Heir of the House of <hi>David. The People answered the King, saying, what Portion have we in</hi> David? <hi>neither have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Son of</hi> Jesse. <hi>To your Tents, O</hi> Israel, <hi>now see to thine House,</hi> David, <hi>v.</hi> 16. After they had thus bidden open Defiance to King <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and were departed to their Tents fully purposed to carry on their Rebellious Enterprise, <hi>Rehoboam</hi> (hoping to appease and reduce them to Obedience) sent <hi>Adoram</hi> to them, but they were so far from hearkning to him, or any Conditions which he had to propose to them, from the King, that they presently <hi>stoned him with Stones, that he dyed;</hi> and if <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had not with all speed <hi>fled
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97880:5"/> in his Chariot to</hi> Jerusalem, they would in all likelihood, have seized his Person, and used him as they should have thought fit, <hi>v.</hi> 18. All this they did under the Conduct of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who headed them at the first, when they went to Petition <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, v.</hi> 3. without doubt therefore they had him in their Eyes from the beginning of their Defection. And so it may be truly said that <hi>this Act of the People (i. e.</hi> Making <hi>Jeroboam</hi> King) <hi>is</hi> both in this place and ii <hi>Chron.</hi> x. 19.) <hi>called Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi> They resisted <hi>Adoram,</hi> because (as they supposed) he was sent to prevent their designs for <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> whom (as it follows in the next <hi>v.</hi>) they immediately, <hi>made King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all</hi> Israel. And now I appeal unto any one, who will impartially consider this History, as it is recorded in the places above mentioned, whether you have not unjustly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd me for wresting of the Scriptures, when I said, that these Illegal and Arbitrary Proceedings of the People in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting their New King, are in Scripture, mark't with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Note of Rebellion?</p>
            <p>Let me now ask you, How you can excuse your self from aequivocating, and wresting the Scriptures to your own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sence, when, upon the Authority of the Prophet <hi>Ahijah</hi>'s Words to <hi>Jeroboam,—Thus saith the Lord, I will take the Kingdom out of his Son's Hand</hi> (i. e. <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s, <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Son) <hi>and give it unto thee, even Ten Tribes,</hi> i King. xi. 5, you affirm, <hi>That</hi> Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, <hi>was a King, by the appointment of Almighty God, though elected by the People?</hi> For what, I ask, do you mean by <hi>the appointment of Almighty God?</hi> That he permitted only this Defection, as a Punishment of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Sin? or that he did positively approve and order it, as much as he did that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> should Succeed in the Throne, after the Death of King <hi>Saul?</hi> If the former; you ought plainly to have said so, that the unwary Reader might not be deceived by an ambiguous Expression. If the later; you must own and defend this false Principle, as grounded upon Scripture — That <hi>Ʋsurpers, and they who in an Hereditary Monarchy ascend the Throne by the People's Defection or Rebellion to their lawful
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97880:6"/> Prince, are as much by God's appointment, as they who possess the Crown by the Right of Hereditary Succession.</hi> God, who sees all things at once, foresaw the People's Sin; which for the Punishment of <hi>Solomon's</hi> Luxury and Idolatry, he suffer'd to come to that height as to ripen into a prosperous Rebellion against <hi>Rehoboam.</hi> This, God was pleas'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal unto his Prophet, and order'd him to tell it unto <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> in these words—<hi>Thus saith the Lord, I will take,</hi> &amp;c.— What is there in these words whence we can infer, that <hi>Jeroboam was a King by the appointment of Almighty God,</hi> any more than we can conclude, from <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s Prophesy, concerning the Captivity of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and the City (<hi>Jer.</hi> xxxiv) that this Captivity was <hi>by the appointment of Almighty God?</hi> the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> was suffered to burn the City and lead <hi>Zedekiah</hi> Captive; but yet in all this, the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> was nevertheless a grievous Tyrant; whose Cruelty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice, God did by no means approve, or positively <hi>appoint,</hi> but only order'd and determined his Wickedness so, as to serve the ends of his Providence, in punishing the Sins of his People.</p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 2.) All the difference betwixt us in this Point is, that you will needs consider the <hi>greatness of the Sovereign,</hi> as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the <hi>publick Detriment;</hi> Whereas I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to joyn the <hi>Sovereign Greatness</hi> and <hi>the Publick Benefit</hi> together, and make these two Friends and Companions to one another. No Sovereign can become really Great by striving to annihilate the well-constituted Government of his Country; neither can any People be happy by opposing and resisting their Sovereign in the Exercise of his just Rights and Prerogatives. <hi>That Maxim, THE SAFETY OF THE PEOPLE IS THE SƲPREME LAW must include</hi> (says Sanderson) <hi>the King in it, and that especially. It supposes there must be an unaccountable Authority in the Prince above all positive human Law; to whom it belongs to foresee and order, that the Commonwealth receive no damage, either through defect of Law, or through the too-superstitious Observation of it.</hi> Prelect. 10. <hi>de Conscient,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97880:6"/>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 3.) In this Section you discourse, methinks, like one who has a mind to say something, though it be never so far from the Subject in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d. We are not here disputing about the Form of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ment, and yet you will needs, by the Head and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lders, bring in your beloved Notion—<hi>That 'tis wholly left to the People to put themselves into this or that Form of Government, which they shall think fit to chuse.</hi> This is besides the business, and is also spoken of in it's proper place. What follows I cannot well reconcile to the Rules of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar. <hi>And all Government whatsoever, though after the mutual Tyes of Reciprocal Oaths, are not joyned by God, though permitted by him.</hi> If there be any meaning of these Words, I suppose it is, that all Government, as to the Form, is indifferent; and that none are bound by their Oaths to maintain the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they live under, longer than it shall be to their good liking. If this be your meaning, I say, that this is not the proper place for you to insist upon this Principle. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less I return this short Answer. 1. That we do not find that God hath any where positively ordain'd any Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but that which is Monarchical. 2. That he who takes an Oath to be true and faithful to any lawful Form of Government, is bound to keep his Oath, till there shall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen an absolute Impossibility of performing; or they to whom he swore, shall loose him from his Obligation.</p>
            <p>But now I am once again to account to this wise Expositor for wresting the Scripture. <hi>But how</hi> (says he) <hi>do you wrest the Scripture?</hi> And what's the Reason of this Emphatical Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation? Only because I apply this saying—<hi>What God hath joyned let no Man put asunder,</hi> to that near Conjunction there is betwixt the Head and the Members in Government, though 'tis indeed particularly spoken with Relation to Man and Wife, <hi>Matth.</hi> xix. 6. But, Sir, if this be to Wrest the Scripture, better and wiser Men than you or I do fall under this Condemnation. Some may call it Wresting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to quote the first Chapter of St. <hi>John</hi> for our Saviour's Divinity. And it seems as irksome to you to hear any Text
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97880:7"/> apply'd to that near Relation there is between the King and his Subjects; as it is to those to see any places of Scripture produc'd for our Lord's Divinity, which contain (as they think) no such thing. This Proposition, <hi>what God hath joyned let no Man put asunder,</hi> is indefinite; and may be properly apply'd to any two Relatives, which God hath joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, by such an <hi>inseparable</hi> Union as is not to be dissolv'd but by himself.</p>
            <p>But, for disputation sake, you're pleas'd to grant, that King and People are joyned together by God. <hi>And upon this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position you argue, that as</hi>
               <q>a Wife may be put away for Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, so may a King forfeit his Right to his People by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to overthrow the Government, and Establish an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Religion.</q> This Argument will do you no Service, till you can produce some Text, wherein God hath as plainly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd a Divorce, betwixt a King and his Subjects, for mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government, as he has in this, betwixt Man and Wife in the case of Fornication. We read of many bad Kings amongst the <hi>Jews,</hi> but we do not find that the People were therefore permitted to depose them; no, not though they endeavoured <hi>to Establish an Idolatrous Religion.</hi> Besides, to make the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment run Parallel, it rather lies thus; an Husband may put away his Wife for the Case of Adultery; therefore the King (who is Head of his People, as the Husband is of his Wife) may cut off an Idolatrous People, from the benefit of his Laws. At the end of this Paragraph you maintain, <hi>that the safety of the Body (i. e.</hi> the People) <hi>is to be valued before the Head (i. e.</hi> the cheif Governour.) And I agree with you, if you can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me, that ever any body can be in health, or indeed can live, without its Head. But you go on; and give us this pleasant Reason for what you say, <hi>Because 'tis an easie matter to get an Head to the Body, but not a Body to the Head.</hi> Now, in my opinion, the one is every jot as easie as the other, and 'tis no less difficult to fit the Head with a Body, then 'tis to match the Body with an Head; that is, if they be once separated, 'tis absolutely impossible in nature to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97880:7"/> find an Head to animate the Body, or a Body to serve the Head; and in Politics, 'twill be found very difficult so to adapt them, that they may live together in Peace, and good Correspondence with one another. The best way therefore is not to divide them; that neither the Head may be forc't to seek its Body, nor the Body its Head. 'Tis usual to cut off a corrupted and gangreen'd Member, when no Cure can be apply'd; but to sever the Head (though it be very sick) from the Body, or divide the whole Body (though full of Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers) from the Head, is such a Method of Cure as never surely was Practised by any Chirurgeon. The Union betwixt them, is so close and necessary, that nothing but Death ought to loose and dissolve it.</p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 4.) All that's here to be consider'd, is, Whether any force or violence have been used to King <hi>James?</hi> You say not, but others (as good Protestants as your self, and who had better opportunity of knowing the Truth in this matter) think o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise. I do assure you, if we have taken up Arms against our Lawful Sovereign, we cannot vindicate our selves either by the Law of the Land, Nature or of Self-preservation. For the proof hereof I refer you to <hi>Sir Edward Cook in his Calvin's Case;</hi> and <hi>the Vindication of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Church, Printed at</hi> Glascoe, <hi>p.</hi> 7, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 10, <hi>p.</hi> 35, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 5.) <hi>The People</hi> (you say) <hi>made the Law the Measure of their Privileges, in the business of the Ship-money.</hi> But how much soever the Law, at the first, might be on their sides, surely you will not deny, but that they stretch't their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges beyond their due Bounds; when they did not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to pay this Tax, but thence also took an occasion to rob the King of all those Prerogatives, wherewith, by Law, he was invested; and at last, of Life it self. Did their Priviledges Authorize them to lift up their hands against his Person, and imbrue them in the Blood of that Glorious Martyr. Suppose that King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>First</hi> was as Arbitrary, and every ways as evil a Prince, as his Rebellious Subjects represented him.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97880:8"/>
               <hi>Yet shall Subjects</hi> (says the Homily against Disobedience. <hi>Part</hi> 1.) <hi>both by their wickedness provo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God, for their deserved punishment, to give them an indiscree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and evil Prince; and also Rebel against him, and withal again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od; who, for the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Sins, did give them su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a Prince?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 6, 7.) In my Answer to your 6th Proposition, I said, that <hi>Kings are God's Vicegerems, and that they who resist them, do resist the Ordinance of God, though the Person be a</hi> Claudius <hi>or a</hi> Nero. I say so still. To disprove this, you tell us, That <hi>a Vicegerent is one that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appointed;</hi> but <hi>Kings</hi> (you say) <hi>are not appointed by God to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the World,</hi> contrary to what you asserted in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> where you say, that even <hi>Jeroboam</hi> himself, <hi>was a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>intment of Almighty God.</hi> But it was not for your turn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y so in this place. For here you are to prove that Kings are not Vicegerents; and therefore in order to this conclusion, you contradict your self, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, <hi>that King's are not appointed by God,</hi> &amp;c. Yet, as if you repented of what you have said, you alter your Note, and in the next Words, allow—<hi>That they may be properly called his Vicegerents, whilst they Administer Justice and Equity to every Man.</hi> But how if one or two, or some few of their Subjects should be wronged by them, must they be degraded, and fall from their Character of being God's Vicegerents for this defect of Justice and Equity? This, methinks, seems a little hard. But to let this pass; I'm glad to find that we are agreed so far. 'Tis some favour however that you'l grant, that <hi>good Kings may be very properly called God's Vicegerents,</hi> though you will not give this Title unto those that are bad, which yet I do not know how you can well deny, if you will own (what you have said) That <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was none of the best of Kings; and yet he was (you say) <hi>a King by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be a Vicegerent is to be in the stead, or to supply the place of another; and accordingly when we say, that Kings are God's Vicegerents, the meaning is, that they Act in his Name, and by his Authority: Which they may do, and yet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97880:8"/> be themselves very bad Men. He who is invested with the Kingly Office, doth in many respects (recited at large by the Lawyers) resemble the Divinity, and is fitly styled God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, when yet he may fail very much in the Duty of his place. But if you will not be satisfied, that your King is God's Vicegerent, unless you can see the very Commission, which he hath immediately received from the hands of God himself, I confess, I know no more how to convince you, than I do an Atheist; who obstinately denies, that there is a God, because he never saw a miracle wrought, whereby his Existence was demonstrated to his Senses. If you be so scrupulous, I doubt, there never was, and never will be any King according to your mind, but such an one, as will acknowledge himself to be not God's, but the Peoples Vicegerent.</p>
            <p>All that follows in this Paragraph, is a Declamation against <hi>Absolute Authority;</hi> which I tell you again, I do attribute to no King upon Earth, nor ever did any Sober Man. I say ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, <hi>That Absolute and unconditionate Obedience is due only to God, who alone hath Absolute Authority.</hi> Nevertheless, the <hi>King as God's Vicegerent,</hi> being the highest Power upon Earth, ought to be obeyed in all things lawful, by a ready compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; in things unlawful, by suffering for Conscience sake, rather than resist by Force of Arms. For, <hi>who can stretch forth his hand against the Lord's Anointed, and be guiltless?</hi> 1 Sam. xxvi. 9.</p>
            <p>As a Comment upon which Text, hear what Bishop <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> says in his Twelfth Sermon <hi>ad Aulam. No conjuncture of circumstances whatsoever, can make that expedient at any time to be done, that is of it's self and in the kind unlawful, for a Man to Blaspheme the Holy Name of God, to Sacrifice to Idols, to give wrong Sentence in Judgment, by his Power to oppress those that are not able to withstand him, by Subtilty to over-reach others in bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to take up Arms (offensive or defensive) against a lawful Sovereign, one of these and sundry other things of like nature being all of them simply,</hi> et de toto genere <hi>unlawful, may not be done by any Man, at any time, in any case, upon any colour or pretension whatsoever;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97880:9"/> the express Command of God himself only excepted, as in the Case of</hi> Abraham <hi>for Sacrificing his Son; not for the avoiding of scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, not at the instance of any Friend, or command of any Power upon Earth. Not for the maintenance of the Lives or Liberties ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our selves or others; not for the Defence of Religion; nor the Preservation of a Church or State; no, nor yet, if that could be imagin'd possible, for the Salvation of a Soul; no, not for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am now to clear my self from an Indictment which you draw up against me, <hi>of making God the Author or Approver of the Ʋsurpations of Men.</hi> This, I do assure you, I do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely deny; and could very easily retort it upon your self, if I should unravel all the pernicious Consequences of your popular Principle. But what you have here said shall not provoke me to it. Perhaps hereafter I may do it, if you shall give me occasion, by persisting in your false Calumnies and Malicious Aspersions. In the mean time, take this short Vindication of my self. God, 'tis most certain, is not the Author of Sin, neither doth he approve any wicked Practices; Yet he who should go about to kill his Father, or any ways to offer violence to him, because he is an habitual Drunkard, or Swearer, or (to come nearer to the Case) a very Tyrant in his Behaviour towards him; This would be not only to resist the Wickednesses, and unjust Rigor of the Father, but also the Ordinance of God; and by all good Christians, would be esteemed a breach of the V. Commandment: And 'tis no less so, I say still, to rise up in Arms against our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince, <hi>though the Person be a</hi> Claudius <hi>or a</hi> Nero. This later (though a Tyrant, a Persecutor, a Murtherer, and what not?) was included in that general Order which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave to the Church. — <hi>Let Prayers and Supplications,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be made for Kings and all that are in Authority,</hi> &amp;c. —And <hi>you must needs be Subject</hi> (said St. <hi>Peter</hi>) though <hi>Domitian</hi> (one every whit as bad as <hi>Claudius,</hi> and almost as ill as <hi>Nero</hi>) was then (as 'tis thought) the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor. The King's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is so absolute, as it makes him unaccountable to his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97880:9"/> People; never so Absolute as to give him a Right, any more than to one of his meanest Subjects, to do Violence, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice to any Man. Absolute Authority, thus understood, did appertain to the Kings of <hi>Israel,</hi> although they were bound to observe the Law, not out of fear of being punish'd for their neglect, by the People, but by God himself. And thus the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> in Conscience towards God, are oblig'd to keep those good and wholsom Laws which are made for the benefit both of King and People, yet (do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your felf) the <hi>English</hi> Presbytery has no more Power over the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> than the Levitical Priesthood had over the Kings of <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Imperial Crown and Jurisdiction of this Realm is</hi> (says Archbishop <hi>Cranmer</hi> in his Letter to Queen <hi>Mary) taken im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from God, to be used under him only, and is Subject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to none but God alone;</hi> Apud Fox. tom. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 672. The People of <hi>England</hi> have no Power to judge their Kings, whether they be good or bad. If they have any such Authority, pray be so kind to your Friends, as to make out their Title; and shew, in what Capacity they may lawfully Exercise this Right. Is it, when some of the chiefest <hi>Daemagogues</hi> are as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled together, and call themselves an <hi>High Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission?</hi> If so, then <hi>Bradshaw</hi> and his Associates did nothing but what was just, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. was in the wrong, when he refus'd to acknowledge their Jurisdiction. But this, I suppose, our Author himself, whatever he thinks, is scarce so hardy, as to maintain. Is this Power lodg'd in a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? That cannot be. For they who have no Power to judge concerning the least Matters, cannot certainly Judge and Condemn the King himself. But if it belongs neither to an High-Commission-Court, nor to a Convention to bind their Kings in Chains, This perhaps may be a priviledge which is peculiar to the <hi>Almighty and uncontroulable MOB.</hi> And truly, when 'tis <hi>lawful for every Man to do that which is lawful in his own Eyes</hi> (the special Prerogative of the <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Mob</hi>) then, and not before, it will be lawful for the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97880:10"/> Multitude, to judge which are good Kings and which are bad ones, and to execute their Judgment upon them, as they shall think fit. Thus, if we consider the People in all their Capacities, we cannot find this Authority in any of them; and therefore we must conclude, that there is, indeed, <hi>no such Power upon Earth;</hi> unless you can perswade us after all, that every such busy Fellow as your self may sit in the Seat of Judicature, and (having pronounc'd the King <hi>Guilty</hi>) loose the People from their Allegiance.</p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11.) The Question (occasioned by your 11th. Maxim, Aphorism or Proposition, chuse how you will have it call'd) is, <hi>whether every Man has the Right of Self-preservation; as intirely under Civil Government, as in a State of Nature?</hi> You hold the Affirmative; I, the Negative. Now in order to come to a resolution in this Point. 1. It would be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to inquire whether indeed there ever was such a <hi>State of Nature,</hi> as you mean, in the World. I confess I much doubt it. For when, I pray, and where? In what Time, and Country, was this <hi>Libertine State</hi> to be found? For my part I never read of any such; neither is it reasonable to believe that God ever placed Men in such a confused State. For he who made all things in Number, Weight and Measure, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver left Men (the best and most beautiful part of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) without Laws and Government, and a mutual depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon one another. <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sons (as soon as they were born) were under the Government of their Father, as his Dominion likewise was over all the other parts of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And had he continued in the State of <hi>Innocence,</hi> this orderly dependance of Inferiors upon their Superiors, would have been so free and unconstrain'd, that there would have been no Violence offer'd to any Man; and so the Principle of Self-preservation would have had nothing to have done in this Golden Age. This therefore cannot be the State of Nature which you mean. And as for that fictitious and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Hypothesis, which <hi>Hobs</hi> lays down as the Ground and Foundation of his Antichristian Politicks, 'tis a meer Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasm
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97880:10"/> (to use one of his own Words) of his own, quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the intention of God and Nature. Yet this Leviathan-State, this Hobbian-Republick must be the State you mean, when you say—<hi>Every Man has the Right of Self preservation as intire, under Civil Government, as in a State of Nature.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing therefore such a <hi>State,</hi> let us, 2. consider the truth of what you say. Now in this State all Men you know have (according to Mr. <hi>Hob</hi>'s Doctrine) a Right to all things; and therefore every Man (in this blessed State) has a Right to kill every other Man, who shall offer to oppose him in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition of his just <hi>Right</hi> (as he thinks it) and not suffer him to become an Universal Proprietor of all the World. Now I hope you will yield that this unlimited Right (or rather boundless Lust) is restrain'd under Civil Government, when the Power of the Sword is lodg'd in the Hands of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magistrate; <hi>For the punishment of Evil doers, and for the praise of them that do well.</hi> Men's private Reason is not now to be their measure in righting or preserving themselves; but the publick Reason of the Community, must give such bounds and limits to their indefinite desires, as may most conduce to the good of the whole. Private Persons (whatever Right of Self-preservation they might have in the State of Nature) after they are incorporated into Civil Society, have no more than the Law doth allow; and that, in all Governments, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Computation, will be found much less than Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi>'s State-of-nature-men do arrogate to themselves.</p>
            <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 12.) You now grow Angry, and breath Vengeance and Antichristian Principles against Passive Obedience; which never did you, nor any body else any harm. Why so furious? Be not so passionate. For (as the <hi>Italian</hi> says) <hi>Molto cattivo geudice è l'affetto. Passion is the worst Judge in the World.</hi> Whilst you give way to it, I can expect neither fair dealing, nor any good Sense from you.—The Point to be examined, is, <hi>whether more Throats have been cut by the Doctrine of Passive Obedience, or that of Resistance?</hi> You say the former has been more guilty, in this Particular. And to prove your Opinion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97880:11"/> you appeal to the Cruel Persecutions under the <hi>Roman</hi> Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, the Massacres of <hi>Paris, Piedmont and Ireland.</hi> Now I am so far from being of your mind, That I do verily believe, that the Doctrine of Passive Obedience did never cut any Man's Throat, and has been always Innocent both in the time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Persecutions, and more modern Massacres. As for the <hi>Roman</hi> Persecutions, The Primitive Christians, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, had deeply imbibed the Doctrine of Passive Obedience. They were fully perswaded, that they could resist without Sin; and therefore pay'd a willing Submission to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Coerceive Power, when they flatly deny'd to do what he Commanded. And thus the Passive Doctrine brought many to the glorious Crown of Martyrdom; but I never read, that it ever cut any one's Throat, or took upon it self, by War and Violence, to dispose the Crowns of this World. You may as well Condemn the Doctrine, <hi>of not doing evil that good may come of it,</hi> for cutting Throats, as this of Submission in all Cases, to the higher Powers. And in truth these two are so nearly related, that they must needs live and dye, stand and fall together.</p>
            <p>As for the Massacres of <hi>Paris, Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> if those Protestants were Butchered for their Religion, when by their unanimous Resistance they might have sav'd themselves, they dye Martyrs in a good Cause. But if the Dragoons and Tories fell upon them on a sudden when they did not expect a Persecution, and were unable to make any Resistance, The Doctrine of Passive-Obedience cannot be Arraign'd, as guilty of their Deaths. Yet woe be to their Persecutors, by whom such an irreparable offence was given to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion.</p>
            <p>But now you come up nearer to me, and suppose at least, the <hi>contrary</hi> (i. e. <hi>that more Throats have been cut by the Doctrine of Resistance, than that of Passive Obedience) but the Sin</hi> (you say) <hi>lies at their doors, who by their cruel Persecutions, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Rights of the People, force them to right themselves.</hi> You mean, force them to Rebel. Now I do affirm, that no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97880:11"/> Man was ever forc'd to commit Sin; and that <hi>Rebellion</hi> is a Sin, all Men must acknowledge, who do not esteem <hi>Witchcraft</hi> as a Vertue. They therefore, who Rebel because the Prince is a Tyrant, and endeavours unjustly to take away their Lives; are far from being guiltless, though they have the greatest Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations imaginable. Such Princes are deservedly odious in the sight of God and Man; yet their Subjects ought not to resist by Force of Arms: For this would be to oppose one Sin by another. And besides, would make it an impossible thing, that there should be any such thing, as <hi>Persecution, for Righteousness-sake.</hi> For when Subjects are too strong for their Prince, they may, nay (according to this Principle) they ought to resist, rather than suffer. And when they are too weak, they suffer only because they cannot help it; which is no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue at all. For there can be no Persecution for Righteousness-sake, which is not undertaken, and endured with Freedom, Chearfulness, and Voluntary Submission to every <hi>Ordinance of Man for the Lord's sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rest of this Section, you spend in raveing, and talking wildly without reason, order and coherence. I have no mind to expose you, though you do give sufficient occasion for a Man to lay you open to the World; as one who has Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed both his Wit and Judgment to his Passion and false Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Government; which Education and Interest, have deeply imprinted on his mind. <hi>We ought not to defend our Religion, when the Laws of the Country are against it.</hi> This is one of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions. Which, I confess, sounds very odly in mine Ears. If we ought <hi>not to defend our Religion, when the Laws of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are against it;</hi> when, I pray, ought we to defend it? But your meaning is, I suppose, that we ought not to defend our Religion <hi>by Force of Arms,</hi> when the Laws of the Country are against it. Neither ought we, after this manner to defend it, <hi>when the Laws of the Country are for it.</hi> But <hi>the Scripture</hi> (you say) <hi>does not require us not to defend our Religion (or civil Rights) Establish'd by the Laws of the Country.</hi> Here you touch this point so tenderly, as if you was conscious, that it will not abide a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97880:12"/> thorough Examination—<hi>The Scripture does not require us not to defend— Our Religion or Civil Rights.</hi> The first of these Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions mollifies your <hi>Doctrine of Resistance</hi> very much. For if <hi>the Scripture does not require us not to defend,</hi> then <hi>the Scripture does not positively require us to defend, &amp;c.</hi> And so we seem to be agreed thus far, that the Doctrine of Resistance is not taught in the Scripture. The second way of expressing your self alters the State of the Question, and makes it altogether ambiguous. <hi>Our Religion or Civil Rights</hi>—as if our Religion and Civil Rights were the same thing; and a Man could not enjoy the one without the other. I wish you would inform us, how this wonderful Transmutation is to be made. If you have an Art to turn Property into Religion, and make <hi>gain to be Godliness,</hi> you ought to be more sought after, than any Chymist of them all, who is <hi>verè adeptus,</hi> and has attain'd the Secret of turning Metals into Gold. But perhaps you may think me too light. To be more serious therefore; I Answer, that the Scripture medles not with Mens Civil Rights: and as for Religion, it has prescrib'd a way to secure it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out such defence, as (in all probability) will ruin both our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Civil Rights. A <hi>Christian boldness in confessing the Truth, and Patient suffering for it, is the best and only lawful means of throwing off the Tyranny and Yoke of Antichrist, if laid upon the Necks of Subjects, by their lawful Sovereigns. (Oxford Ʋniversity's</hi> Reasons against the Covenant drawn up by Bishop <hi>Sanderson p.</hi> 210, 211.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if we may not defend our Religion, any Army or Number of Heathens may come, and settle their false Religion here.</hi> No, Sir! 'Tis lawful and our Duty to resist a Foreign Prince, who unjustly Invades his Neighbours Country, let his pretence be what it will. But if our Religion and Rights should be Invaded by our own lawful Prince, then earnest Prayers to God, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Supplications to the King, unfeigned Repentance, and Amendment of our Lives are the only proper Weapons of our Christian Defence. <hi>If a Foreign Power</hi> (says Dr. C.) <hi>opposes our King, he is a Robber: If he be a Subject, who rises against his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97880:12"/> Sovereign, he hath renounc'd Christianity with his Allegiance, and is to be esteemed a Troubler of our</hi> Israel. <hi>Therefore whatsoever they be that are Enemies to the King, and whatsoever the pretence be, we wish they may never prosper. Comp.</hi> to the Temple, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 177. Thus doth this worthy Author An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer both your Cases—<hi>that of a Foreign Prince, and that of our own Sovereign.</hi> And as to the later, that is, <hi>the point of Resistance, if our Religion and Rights should be Invaded,</hi> by our own Prince; be pleas'd to consult the <hi>D. of C's. Excellent Letter to the Lord</hi> Russel.</p>
            <p>The eminent Man of whom you have heard (and whose Name you seem to be ignorant of, tho' you Appeal to his Book) was one <hi>Lucifer Calaritanus,</hi> who wrote a Book <hi>de Regibus Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staticis;</hi> wherein he has spoken some things which shew him to have been a Person of more zeal and warmth, than tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Christian moderation. This Book I do not find ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by St. <hi>Athanasius,</hi> as containing Orthodox Doctrine; though he did indeed recommend the Two Books, which were Written by the same Author, in behalf of himself against the Emperor <hi>Constantius:</hi> But these Books were Written before <hi>Julian the Apostate</hi> came to the Empire; and so could not be occasioned by his telling the Christians, <hi>that their Doctrine was to suffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus made some Reflections upon your loose and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coherent Sayings, I should now examin your Interpretation of several Texts of Scripture; which Province I wish you would leave unto those who are better able to manage it. Let a <hi>Socinian</hi> be the Interpreter, and the Scripture shall speak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his Sense. And if one of Seditious Principles be allow'd to comment upon the Bible, we shall be sure to find nothing therein but comfortable Doctrine for those <hi>who despise Dominion, and speak evil of Dignities.</hi> I shall here insert your Explications of the Texts alledged in one Column, and their true meaning (as the most Ancient and Orthodox Expositors have understood them) in another; that the Reader may have an Antidote against your Poyson.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="paraphrase">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97880:13"/>
                        <head>The Author's Comment or Paraphrase.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHere the Word of a King is</hi> (according to the Law or Custom of the Country) <hi>there is Power, and who may say unto him, what do'st thou?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Submit your selves to every Law of Man, <hi>for the Lord's sake, whether it be to the King</hi> as cheif Executor of the Laws, or unto Officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the King, for the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting, or fulfilling of the Laws.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Let every Soul be Subject</hi> to the Laws, or Customs of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and to the Prince as Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor thereof: For the greatest Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain amongst Mankind, acts by the Power of Almighty God; but not by his Appointment, or Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. The Power which every Man hath, is from God. <hi>They</hi> therefore <hi>that resist</hi> the Laws, <hi>resist</hi> the Powers (beyond which a Prince hath no Power)—<hi>For he is the Minister of God for good,</hi> whilst he administers Justice, and Equity to every Man; and punisheth him that doth evil, or violates the Laws. Wherefore ye must needs (if the Laws be against you) suffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of the Country, though never so unreasonable. Render therefore to all their Dues; Tribute, Custom, Fear and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom it is due by the Laws of the Land.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="observations">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97880:13"/>
                        <head>Observations <hi>upon the</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Expositions.</head>
                        <p n="1">I. I Observe upon his first Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase, That (which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self confesses) the King's of <hi>Israel</hi> were absolute and unaccountable to the People, for their Actions; whether they were good or bad; whether they were according to the Law of God <hi>(the only Law and Custom of that Country)</hi> or no: And therefore their Commands, 'tis plain, were not to be disputed <hi>ore gladij, by the Sword's point,</hi> though they were never so unjust: And consequently though the Author's Exposition is true, yet it is not full, and doth not reach the true intent and meaning of the Words.</p>
                        <p>I Observe II. That if St. <hi>Peter by every ordinance of Man,</hi> means <hi>every Law of Man,</hi> then the Words must run thus—<hi>Submit your selves to every Law of Man for the Lord's sake; whether it be to the King as the Supream Law, &amp;c.</hi> And if this be so, what will become of the People's Title to judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne their King? Thus our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor outwits himself, and in effect destroys the Principle, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to maintain. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> I suppose his meaning is, that both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97880:14"/> the Laws and King's are made by the People, and are both so far to be submitted unto, as they have the People's consent, and good likeing; and no farther. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will this Comment agree with the Text. For thus, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle should rather have exprest him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self after this manner. <hi>Submit your selves to every Law of Man</hi> (not <hi>for the Lord's,</hi> but) <hi>for the Peoples sake,</hi> so that still we are at a loss, how to make the Words hit with our Author's Sense: And we are more to seek, how to make them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with St. <hi>Paul's:</hi> who expresly teaches, <hi>that there is no Power but of God.</hi> But our Expositor is, I believe, not much concern'd whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther St. <hi>Peter</hi> be consistent, either with himself, or his Brother Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle St. <hi>Paul;</hi> 'tis enough, he thinks, if he can but hale his Words into his own Opinion, and fit them to that System of Government, which he hath form'd to himself; which yet, he hath not done.</p>
                        <p>I Observe III. That in his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase upon St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Words, he will needs still divide the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> betwixt the Laws, and the Prince; whereas nothing is more plain, then that the Apostle speaks of Men (and not Laws) invested with Regal Authority. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He seems to insinuate, that the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the meanest Person, is as much from God, as that of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, Independent Prince. <hi>The Power</hi> (says he) <hi>which every Man
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97880:14"/> hath is from God. Thirdly,</hi> He has thought fit to say nothing at all to the great Sanction, of this Christian Law, concerning Submission to the Supream Authority — <hi>And they that resist, shall receive to themselves damnation.</hi> This was too hot for him to touch. I pray God, that he may never feel the smart of it hereafter. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He tells us, we <hi>must needs suffer according to the Laws of the Country (if they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us) tho never so unreasonable.</hi> Now for my part, I think there is little difference, whether a Man suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers by <hi>unreasonable Laws,</hi> or the Arbitrary and <hi>unreasonable Edicts of a Sovereign Prince,</hi> as the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians did. Nay, If I must suffer, I should rather chuse the later than the former way. For <hi>unreasonable Laws</hi> (if made by the general consent of the People) shew, that the generality of the People are so too, who would consent to such Laws; and therefore 'tis not probable that they will, in a little time, be brought to acknowledge their Error, and repeal these <hi>unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Laws;</hi> so that a Man may languish under them, as long as he lives, and his posterity after him, without any redress. But a <hi>Sovereign Prince</hi> is but one Person; and he, it's likely, may more easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be perswaded to revoke his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable Edicts;</hi> or Death may take him off, and prevent him (sooner than a Body of Men) from Executing what he designs. <hi>Fifthly</hi>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97880:15"/> and <hi>Lastly,</hi> our Author makes no difference betwixt <hi>Obedience and Subjection,</hi> which he ought to do. For thus all pretence of Resistance will be taken away, and yet the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject secur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rom committing Sin, by an actual Obedience to any <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> or unlawful Command. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if Absolute Submission be not a Duty, when active Obedience is not, we may resist by Force of Arms; and <hi>so, do evil that good may come of it;</hi> directly contrary bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> to the Apostolical Precept, and Practise.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="texts">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97880:13"/>
                        <head>The Texts of Scripture.</head>
                        <p>WHere the Word of a King is, there is Power; and who may say unto him, what do'st thou? <hi>Eccles. viii. 4.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Submit your selves to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Man, for the Lord's sake; whether it be to the King as Supream; or unto Governors, as unto them that are sent by him; for the punishment of Evil Doers, and for the praise of them that do well. <hi>1 Pet. 11, 13, 14.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers. For there is no Power, but of God. The Powers that be, are ordain'd of God. Who so therefore resisteth the Ordinance of God; and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation. For Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are not a Terror to good Works, but to the evil. Wilt thou not be afraid of the Power? Do that which is good; and thou shal't have praise of the same. For he is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of God to thee for good: But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid: For he beareth not the Sword in vain: For he is the Minister of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil. Wherefore ye must needs be Subject, not only for wrath, but Conscience sake; for this cause pay you tribute also: For they are God's Ministers attending continually upon this very thing. Therefore render to all their Dues;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97880:13"/> Tribute to whom Tribute is due; Custom to whom Custom; Fear to whom Fear; Honour to whom Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Rom. xiii. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="observations">
                        <p>This Doctrine of Obedience, the <hi>Author of the enquiry into the present State of Affairs,</hi> calls St. <hi>Paul's Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stem of Government;</hi> as if the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle made Systems of Government, as the Astronomers do of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. This expression seems a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle too light and Philosophical in so serious a matter. But that which is more remarkable, is, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving set down these Seven Verses, as if they were self-evident and needed no further Explication, he only adds his decisive Judgment upon them, as follows—<hi>in these Words we have the Duty of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, as well as the Obedience of the Subject set forth, and so mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that we must conclude, that upon the Total failing of the one, the other does likewise cease.</hi> The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty indeed of the Magistrate as well as the Obedience of the Subject, is set forth in these Words; but here's not a Word of the <hi>Subjects Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ceasing,</hi> if the <hi>Magistrate</hi> shall not perform his <hi>Duty.</hi> Nay, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 'tis evident, had no design to teach any such Doctrine, but only to lay down a certain and Eternal Rule of Christian Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the <hi>Supream Powers,</hi>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97880:14"/> though they <hi>did</hi> never so much abuse their Power. For had his intent been to have inculcated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them this Principle — <hi>That Obedience ceases, upon the Total Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Magistrate to perform his Duty;</hi> he would in effect, have Preach't to them Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, instead of Submission and Obedience. For the Emperor, then in Possession, was one of the worst, that ever was; and if ever any Prince, Totally fail'd in his Duty, he certainly did. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, that he was so very bad, he gives them not the least li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to disobey; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary puts them in mind, more than once, of that <hi>good</hi> which they did and might receive under his Government, though he himself, was one of the worst of Men.— But if Obedience do <hi>Totally cease</hi> upon the <hi>Total failing</hi> of he Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate to perform his Duty, I would gladly know when it may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, that the Magistrate doth <hi>Totally</hi> fail in his Duty? Is it, when he notoriously violates the Law of Nature? No, that cannot be: For the Emperor, when this Epistle to the <hi>Romans</hi> was Written, did so, in the highest degree. Is it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he Persecutes Christianity? Not this neither: For this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror did so. Is it, because he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to subvert the Laws of the Land? Not so neither: For how can this be a greater Crime, than the notorious violations of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97880:14"/> Laws of Nature, and the Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Christianity. What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this <hi>Total failure,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth it consist? Surely it can be nothing else but when a Prince is Totally depriv'd either of Reason, or of Life. And in this Sense I grant the Subjects Obedience to that Individual Person must needs <hi>cease.</hi> We are then at last come to this, that in case of Lunacy, or Phrensy, or Death, the Subjects Obedience <hi>ceases,</hi> and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. The last of these doth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally dissolve the Relation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Prince and the People; and the other two by a moral necessity; if by many, repeated and habitual actions they can be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably proved in the Face of the whole World; yet so, as that, where the Government is heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, it shall be put into the hands of a Guardian, one or more; as in the Case of Infancy. But now none of these Cases will serve the design of the <hi>enquiry.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the business was done as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, as if he, who stood in the way betwixt some Person's Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and the Crown, had been either an Ideot or a Madman; in his Cradle, or his Grave. But it was at this time necessary to tell the People, that <hi>the Magistrate had Totally fail'd in his Duty:</hi> And then <hi>we must,</hi> forsooth! <hi>needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> (not from St. <hi>Paul's Words</hi> which intimate no such thing, but from our <hi>own lusts,</hi> which we call
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97880:15"/> the <hi>necessity of present Affairs</hi>) that upon the <hi>Total failing of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate's Duty, the Subject's Obedience does likewise cease.</hi> But <hi>my Soul! come not thou into their Secrets.</hi> And may I never be one of those <hi>jolly Casuists,</hi> who to serve a present turn, will at least, endanger not only the <hi>damnation</hi> of themselves, but their Neighbours also. I confess, that I have not <hi>strength of thought</hi> enough, to manage such an hardy enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise, as this is.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The true <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Meaning</hi> of these <hi>Places of Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHere the Word of a King is, there is Power;</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a Sovereign Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from one who Acts in the Name, and by the Authority of God Almighty, <hi>And who may say unto him what do'st thou?</hi> And who can call him to an account for his Actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Submit your selves to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man,</hi> if you cannot active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obey, yet at least submit your selves to all Superiour Magistrates, <hi>for the Lord's sake</hi> (by whose Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they Act) <hi>whether it be to the King</hi> (next under God) in all Causes and over all Persons, <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream; or unto Governors, as unto them, that are sent by him,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Commissioned by him <hi>for the punishment of evil doers, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for the praise of them that do well:</hi> The end for which both the King and his Ministers are appointed by God; which yet, if they shall not fulfil, you must nevertheless <hi>Submit, for the Lord's sake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers.</hi> Let every Person, of what quality, rank and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion soever, be Subject to the King and his Subordinate Ministers. <hi>For there is no Power but of God.</hi> For both the King (or Emperor) and they who Act under him, are Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by God himself. <hi>The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that be, are ordain'd of God.</hi> The Emperor and his Ministers are (I say again) invested with their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by the God of Order. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so therefore resisteth the Power</hi> (they who by force and violence, oppose
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97880:15"/> the Emperor and his Ministers) <hi>resisteth the Ordinance of God</hi> (do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose or fight against that Order which God himself hath Establish'd amongst Men) <hi>And they that resist shall receive to themselves damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And they that do thus oppose God in his Ministers, shall be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely judged. This free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Subjection is a good Work; and though you may suffer by it, yet having the Testimony of a good Conscience, you will have no cause to fear the Magistrates Power: <hi>For Rulers are not a terror to good Works but to the evil.</hi> For not they who do good, but they who do evil, have reason to be afraid of their Governors— <hi>Wil'st thou then not be afraid of the Power?</hi> Wil'st thou behave thy self so, as not to have any just fear of thy Rulers Power? <hi>Do that which is good.</hi> Act as a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian ought to do in all Cases; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this instance, of dutiful Submission to the Emperor, and all in Authority under him; <hi>And thou shalt have praise of the same.</hi> By this means thou wil'st, it's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable (however thou oughtest to) <hi>gain</hi> his favour. <hi>For He is the Minister of God to thee for good.</hi> For the Power which God hath given him, is design'd for thy encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in well doing: <hi>But if thou do that which is evil</hi> (by resisting his Power, and other evil practises) <hi>Be afraid</hi> (thou hast cause to be afraid) <hi>For he beareth not the Sword in vain,</hi> which he would do, did he not punish all Rebellious, and wicked practises of what kind so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. <hi>For he is the Minister of God, a Revenger to Execute wrath upon him that doth evil</hi> (whether by resisting his Authority, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise) <hi>wherefore ye must needs be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> (so that there is a necessity of this Absolute Submission) <hi>not only for wrath, but Conscience sake</hi> (not only for fear of punishment, but out of the Sense of your Duty, which you owe to your Sovereign Prince, for the Lord's sake) <hi>For, for this Cause, pay you Tribute also:</hi> Now, that you ought to submit not only for fear of Punishment, but for Conscience sake, appears from the Taxes which are Levy'd upon you, and which you're oblig'd in Duty to pay: <hi>For they are God's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters attending continually upon this very thing.</hi> For (once more I tell you) all Sovereign Powers are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by God for the good of the World, which they ought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to attend—<hi>Render there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to all their Dues; Tribute to whom Tribute is due; Custom to whom Custom; Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour.</hi> Render therefore unto all what justly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto them; <hi>Trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, Custom, Fear and Honour</hi> to the Emperor and his Ministers; unto whom they are more especially <hi>due,</hi> both by the Divine and Imperial Laws.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97880:16"/>
               <p>And now for a more full answer to your Paraphrase, and all that follows in this long Paragraph, I refer you to the Reverend D. <hi>P's</hi> Paraphrase, upon Proverbs; which you'l find faithfully quoted in the History of <hi>Passive Obedience, p.</hi> 84. —And since my saying, <hi>This is right Commonwealth Rhetoric,</hi> hath chaft you into all this heat, and made you spend so many unnecessary words, let me direct you to another Learned Author who runs the Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel between the deposing Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Commonwealth Principles, in these Three Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. (1.) In setting up a Court of Judicature over Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes. (2.) In breaking the Oaths and Bonds of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance Men had entered into. (3.) In justifying Rebellion on the account of Religion. <hi>Jesuite's Loyalty. History</hi> of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> p. 133.</p>
               <p>I shall now leave the Impartial Reader to judge, whether you or I may be justly charg'd for having wrested the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Nay, Sir, be your self the Judge, whether I have not given the true and genuine Interpretation of these Texts? And whether you be not <hi>Self-condemn'd,</hi> and a <hi>Wrester of Scripture</hi> by your own Rules? Your charge runs in these words. —<hi>What a Sin are you and all other Men for Passive Obedience Guilty of, that wrest the Scriptures, which were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Suffering State of Christianity, whilst under Heathen Princes and without Laws to support them; and compare them to the present Circumstances?</hi> Here you manifestly yield, that the Interpretation of the Scriptures, which most favours the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Passive-Obedience, is most agreeable to the <hi>Suffering State of Christianity, whilst under Heathen Princes, and without Laws to support them.</hi> Now 'tis certain, that all the whole New Testament was Written during this <hi>Suffering State of Christianity.</hi> Judge therefore, whether they who interpret it in this Sense, do not give the true, proper, immediate and genuine Meaning of it or no? If it be to wrest the Scriptures, to explain and apply them as they were intended, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we who are for <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> are Guilty of this Sin,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97880:16"/> but if this be to deal truly and faithfully with Men in the great Concern of their Souls, then we are not to blame: but those cannot be excused, who, to serve a turn, Wrest and Wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Scriptures from their <hi>Original and Primitive Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> as if there was one Sense of them for the <hi>Suffering State of Christianity,</hi> and another for the <hi>present Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 13.) The People (I agree) are not bound actively to obey any Commands of their Prince, which are repugnant to the Laws of God and the Land.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 14.) <hi>The Oath of Allegiance,</hi> or <hi>Corporation Oath</hi> (after all your tossing and tumbling to cast it off) sticks close to you; and (like a faithful Monitor) is continually at your El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, to warn you, that you must never rebel, let the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be what it will. What can be more plain, than the words themselves—I do swear, <hi>&amp;c. That it is not lawful upon any pretence whatsoever to take up Arms,</hi> &amp;c. Yet this Oath (you may be sure) was not designed for our ruine. It doth indeed cut off all hopes of destroying the Monarchy, if Men would keep their Oaths; and to such as are given to change, it may indeed be grievous, but to none others, who desire <hi>to live quiet and peaceable Lives in all godliness and honesty.</hi> This Oath doth not (as you would have us to believe) make the King a Tyrant by Law, neither doth it allow him to be such: but it hinders Subjects from being Rebels, and will not allow them to be such against all Law, Reason and Christianity. <hi>For a Rebel is worse than the worst Prince, and Rebellion is worse than the worst Government of the worst Prince that hitherto hath been. Hom.</hi> against <hi>Obed. Part.</hi> 1. In short, this Oath is agreeable to the Doctrine of our Church ever since the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. <hi>No Subjects may draw their Swords against their Prince for any cause whatsoever it be;</hi> say <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Redman</hi> and other Worthies of our Church, <hi>in their Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Christian Doctrine,</hi> An. 1537.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 15.) <hi>If Negative Resistance</hi> (as you here define) <hi>is to disobey the Commands of the Prince, when according to Law,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97880:17"/> Then <hi>David</hi> by flying from <hi>Saul</hi> (which you say in your first Paper, was his negative Resistance) did disobey <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, when according to Law.</hi> How these things can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd I desire to be inform'd. As for <hi>David</hi>'s 600 Men, though they might not be all intended for Spies and Scouts; yet the overplus might be no more than one in his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances (being Heir apparent to the Crown) might reasonably keep about him for his Guard. As for <hi>Athaliah,</hi> 'tis sure, that she was an Usurper, and 'tis most probable, that therefore she was depos'd, and not for Murthering the King's Sons, and her other Acts of Cruelty: for many other Princes were very cruel and unjust, and yet we do not read that they were depos'd.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 16.) <hi>Neither an Invasion actually made, nor eminently feared by a Foreign Power, doth Authorize Subjects to depose their King.</hi> This is my Proposition. To which you answer? <hi>We have not depos'd the King,</hi> &amp;c. That he is, by force, dispossest of his Throne 'tis certain, call it by what new Term of Art you please. However we may endeavour to palliate the matter, the Papists (we may be sure) will say, 'tis neither better nor worse than <hi>Deposing our King;</hi> and that, we do now seem to be agreed with them in this Point; how severely soever we have formerly condemn'd it. And I am sorry, That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, and Protestants, and Church-of-England-men, should give them this occasion to account us their Proselytes, by the Practice of that Doctrine, wherein we were before, so visibly distinguish'd. <hi>Hoc Ithacus velit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if King</hi> James (you tell us) <hi>had kept the Law, he never had lost his Rights,</hi> &amp;c. Sir! neither you nor I know this; for they who neither love nor fear their King, will always find some pretence or other to be rid of him, whether <hi>he keeps the Law or not.</hi> But taking it for granted, that King <hi>James</hi> did <hi>violate the Law</hi> in as high a degree as you would perswade us he did: Is this a sufficient Warrant for us to break the Law and our Oaths too? Where then is our <hi>Subjection for Conscience sake?</hi> Where is our <hi>Obedience for the Lord's sake?</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97880:17"/> This is a Doctrine, <hi>which we ought heartily to detest as false and scandalous in the Supposition; and in the Inference seditious and devilish.</hi> How defective soever the King may be in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his part, this doth not excuse our neglect, or discharge us from our Obligations.</p>
               <p>The publick quiet and safety requires, that he who robs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man, or fires an House, should suffer Death for so doing. But that it is for the publick benefit, that Kings should be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to their Subjects, and punish'd by them for their Misdemeanours, this I utterly deny, unless you can shew, that it is for the publick good, to act directly contrary to God's Commandment. 'Tis a greater Evil (all things consider'd) to depose bad Kings, than to suffer the ill Consequences of their Misgovernment: and besides, 'tis Rebellion against God himself as well as his Vicegerent. And notwithstanding what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Holiness Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and the Reverend Fathers of the Society have Taught or Practis'd to the contrary; This is, and ever will be a most certain truth; <hi>For Subjects to resist their Sovereign Prince upon any pretence whatsoever, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful and impious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your silly and improper instance <hi>of a Father's disinheriting his Eldest Son,</hi> is not worth taking notice of. It supposes forsooth, the People to be the Father, and the King, as their Son; A good Child indeed, so long as he behaves himself as he ought to do; otherwise the Rod is ready for him, and he must be whip'd. I am asham'd of such indecent and fulsom Comparisons. I agree, that <hi>Our Constitution is the happiest in the World;</hi> but by such State-menders as your self, I pray God, it doth not become one of the worst in Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>If all be true, that you say, of King <hi>James—That he took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the whole Authority—That he made himself the sole Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Government—That he govern'd by his Absolute Will and Pleasure,</hi> &amp;c. Yet from all these Premises, it doth not follow— <hi>That his Subjects are absolv'd from the Oath of Allegiance, as much as if he was actually dead, and had sign'd a Resignation of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97880:18"/> his Crown.</hi> For the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is Imperial, and no Forfeiture can be made, by any degree of Male-Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration. The King of <hi>England</hi> is as much a King before he has taken the Coronation-Oath, as after: And if he shall neglect to perform it, after he has taken it, the Government doth not therefore lapse to the People. And to argue otherwise, is to reason like a Man, who neither understands the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Rights of our Kings, nor the Duty of his Subjects. The Regal Authority remains, though the King abuses his Power; and the Duty of Subjects is not dissolv'd, though he extends his Authority beyond the just Rights of a King.</p>
               <p>In the next place, you fall upon the Topick of <hi>Resignation, and Desertion of the Government.</hi> This Argument has been so throughly skan'd, and so judiciously manag'd by the <hi>Author of the Desertion discus'd,</hi> that it seems to be wholly forsaken. Your ablest Pens cannot maintain this Cause: Let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore advise you by no means to undertake it. Before you ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture so dogmatically to determine, that, what King <hi>James</hi> did was a <hi>publick Resignation of his Throne to the Nation;</hi> you should consult the Historians for some Parallel Instance, which has been adjudg'd, and generally receiv'd as a Resignation. But because you present us with no such Example, I shall take it for granted, that there is none of that Nature; at least, that you know of none such. The Case of <hi>Edward</hi> the IV. seems to have been the most like that of King <hi>James;</hi> and yet it was never judg'd to have been a Desertion, Resignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Abdication; neither was it ever call'd by any of these hard Names. I shall give it you, as 'tis related by <hi>Philip de Comines,</hi> a Person of good Account amongst the Historians both for his Judgement and Integrity. He tells us, that, <hi>Edward</hi> the IV. being deserted by his Soldiers, was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd by the increasing greatness of the Earl of <hi>Warwick:</hi> That therefore he was forc'd, for his own Security, to make his escape into <hi>Holland</hi> first, and afterwards into <hi>Burgundy:</hi> That, he soon after returned into <hi>England;</hi> And, though he brought no great Force with him, yet by the revolt of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97880:18"/> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> (King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Brother) with 12000 Men from the Earl of <hi>W.</hi> to the King's Party, he becam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> so strong, that he defeated the Earl in a pitch'd Battle; and in 21 Days recovered his Kingdom, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Earl of <hi>W.</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him in Eleven. Now the Plea of Abdication or Desertion was never made use of against King <hi>Edward</hi> the IV. though it might, as plausibly, have been objected against him, as it is now against King <hi>James</hi> the II. For he went away (as appears by the story) with as great Precipitation, and as much Surprise to his People, as King <hi>James</hi> did. And he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed no body to officiate in his stead, when he was gone; neither did he take any care for the Administration of the Government in his absence, <hi>Phil. Comin. p.</hi> 92, 93, 94, &amp;c. <hi>Engl. Edict.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You go on, and ask, <hi>What can be said for</hi> Scotland? I also put the same Question. And you must give us a more satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Answer, than you have yet return'd to it, or we must conclude that in truth, <hi>nothing can be said for</hi> Scotland; with what forehead can you say that King <hi>James</hi> was never lawful King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> if he never took the Coronation-Oath? Has it not always been an undoubted Truth received by our Lawyers, <hi>That the King of Great Britain, is so, before he has taken the Oaths?</hi> As for that <hi>Absolute Authority,</hi> by which, you say, he govern'd in <hi>Scotland;</hi> upon inquiry, I believe, it will not be found so Absolute, as you would rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sent it; and, if it was; whether it was therefore <hi>reasonable as well as necessary, to throw off this Arbitrary and Ʋnlawful Governour,</hi> you, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, are not so well vers'd in the Constitution of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as that we may securely rely upon your Judgment in the Case.</p>
               <p>And the same Question, which you put about <hi>Scotland,</hi> you may also propose concerning <hi>Ireland.</hi> For the <hi>Irish</hi> (when the King left <hi>England,</hi> were (as at other times) governed by his Deputy-Leiutenant, and so his going away could have no Impression upon that Nation. Thus have you raised Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which all that you're able to say, can never conjure down again.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97880:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well! but if no Forfeiture can be made, what must be done? what Anarchy? what Confusion? what Ruine and Destruction to the utter extirpation of our Civil Rights and Religion, destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many</hi> 1000 <hi>Souls,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>must have follow'd?</hi> In answer to all which, I could easily represent the Tragical Consequences of <hi>Deposing,</hi> in a much more dismal Dress. All these sad things which you mention, <hi>Anarchy, Confusion, Ruine, the loss of our Civil Rights and Religion, destruction of many</hi> 1000 <hi>Souls,</hi> will inevitably follow the deposing Practice; besides, that which is more to be fear'd than all these, <hi>Eternal Damnation.</hi> 'Tis needless to enlarge upon this Subject; both you and I have <hi>talk'd</hi> more, than the Reader (if he has not very little to do) will have cause to thank us for. Yet I cannot conclude this Section without taking notice, of that unbecoming Irony, which you pass upon the Prayers and Patient Submission of the Church, in the Case of a bad Prince; who will not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his Oath. <hi>We must</hi> (say you) <hi>e'ne have set down and cryed, Lord have mercy upon us, and expect</hi> (have expected) <hi>our deliverance by Miracle, though Miracles are ceas'd.</hi> Sir! you seem to be a Man not much given to Wit; and I wish (for your own sake as well as Christianity in general) that you had not vented it upon this occasion. <hi>Though Miracles are ceas'd,</hi> yet the Doctrine of our Blessed Saviour and his Apostles do still remain and shall continue for ever. <hi>Though Miracles are ceass'd,</hi> yet, I hope you will not say, that God's Providence is also <hi>ceas'd.</hi> Tho <hi>Miracles are ceas'd,</hi> yet his care over his Church is not <hi>ceas'd.</hi> Had we <hi>sate down and cry'd, Lord, have mercy upon us,</hi> as we ought to have done; God would have been glorified by our Sufferings; and, in his good time, he would have rescu'd us from them, <hi>without a Miracle.</hi> When the edge of Sovereign Authority is turn'd against us, then to <hi>cry unto the Lord in our distress,</hi> is no such despicable means of Deliverance as you may imagine. I have read of some Tyrants, who have been more afraid of the Prayers of good Men, than of all the armed force of their Enemies; but I never met with any good Christian, who trusted more to his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97880:19"/> Temporal, than his Spiritual Weapons; and thought it in vain to betake himself to his Prayers, if he might not, at the same time, second them with his Sword. Believe me, Sir, or rather beleive the whole Primitive Church, that there can be no better opposition against a Tyrant, than the <hi>amendment of our Lives, and constant Prayers to God. Though Miracles are ceas'd,</hi> yet, for the sake of our common Christianity, do not despise, a <hi>Lord! have mercy upon us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 17.) Here you state the difference betwixt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a Private Person and a King. And, if your Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks hold good, 'tis only this—<hi>That a Private Person has no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority at all, but to live according to the Laws; whereas a King is an Executor of the Laws.</hi> A wonderful discovery! for which surely you expect no less, than that all Kings should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you their thanks; and reward you, for this great Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I would fain (as you tell me) set the King above the Laws, but I'm sure <hi>your Hypothesis</hi> places him under them. I had thought that 'tis the Prince, who gives life and breath to the Law, and that his <hi>Le Roy Le Veut,</hi> signifies something more than to be a meer Executor of the Law; which every petty Constable is, in his proper District. The King, 'tis true, is Executor of the Laws; but let it be always remember'd, that he is <hi>Supreme Executor and Legislator</hi> too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 18, 19. The matter to be inquired into, is, What makes a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>real</hi> King? I say, <hi>he that ascends the Throne by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Title, is a true and real King.</hi> No, say you. <hi>'Tis Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, taking the Coronation-Oath and governing according to Law, which makes a true and real King.</hi> Let the matter be argued; 'Twill be granted, I suppose, that he is a <hi>true and real</hi> King, whose Title is neither Defective, nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; and that his Title who comes regularly to the Throne is thus qualified. I conclude therefore that such an one is a <hi>true and real</hi> King. As for <hi>Possession, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Coronation-Oath, governing according to Law,</hi> these Titles, taken either separately or altogether, do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all defect, and counterfeit. A Man may take Possession
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97880:20"/> by Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lence; He may swear to govern according to Law, and also Rule according to his Oath; yet his Title may be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fective, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat of the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> was; and it may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, as <hi>Simnel</hi>'s and <hi>Warbeck</hi>'s had been, had these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ever been crown'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for your Instances of <hi>Sigisbert</hi> King of <hi>W. Saxons,</hi> that of <hi>Edw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> the II. and the other of <hi>Richard</hi> the II. 'tis not two or three Presidents in 7 or 800 Years time, that can make a Right; much less can these Examples (always condemn'd but when they serve a turn) prejudice the Ancient Law, Custom and Manner of the Kingdom. As for <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. he did not openly disavow reigning in the Right of his Wife. The Act of Parliament, by which he was recognised King of <hi>England,</hi> was capable of this Interpretation, as the Lord <hi>Bac.</hi> observes in his <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. and so, by this Constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no Injury was done to the Hereditary Right of the Crown. Besides, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Queen <hi>de jure,</hi> made no Claim, and consequently, did tacitly resign, which seemed to make him <hi>de jure,</hi> as well as <hi>de facto</hi> King. The Law (which you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in <hi>Edward the Confessor</hi>'s Reign, you must know, good Sir! is no Law, unless you reckon the saying of a Pope to be so. For this (as I am inform'd) is no more. And if you once begin to obtrude the Dictates of his Holiness for Laws upon the Nation, upon my word, your Cause will suffer by it; and you must have a care, that you be not answered with a <hi>Praemunire</hi> from <hi>Westminster-hall.</hi> By the Clause in King <hi>Henry's Charter,</hi> you mean, perhaps, that in King <hi>John</hi>'s quoted in the Pastoral Letter, out of the Original Articles; as we are told. However this is more to your purpose; and I shall therefore consider it. Now. 1. This was King <hi>John's</hi> own Grant; and therefore cannot be pleaded as the original Right of the People. 2. It was a Grant extorted by Force and Violence; and therefore transfers no legal, and regular Right. 3. It was the Grant of a King, whose Misery, or Pusillanimity, or both, made him formally resign his Crown into the hands of the Pope; and therefore, 'tis no wonder, that he should
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97880:20"/> subject himself to the Barons, and People of <hi>England;</hi> as the most likely way to shake off his Sovereign Master, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging his Subjects to stand by him in the recovery of his lost Rights and Reputation, It was the Popish Yoke, which then lay heavy upon his Shoulders, and sunk him thus low; And to argue, that what he did, in this forlorn Condition, ought to be a Law to all his Successors, is a Popish Conclusion, drawn from Popish Premises; and does not become those, who would be esteemed the great Advocates of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion. And indeed, all the Precedents which you, after others, make use of, to uphold your tottering Cause, are drawn from those times, wherein Popery was Predominant in <hi>England,</hi> as well as in other places; and therefore ought not to weigh with us now, who do not stand upon that bottom.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 20.) The Oath mentioned, <hi>Eccles.</hi> viii. 2. was the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> and (if you will) <hi>of Supremacy too,</hi> which the People took to the King, by and with the approbation of God himself. This Oath we all have, or ought to have, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and we have called God to witness the truth of our Intentions, Endeavours and Resolutions to perform this Oath: and if we dare for any respect whatsoever, violate this Oath; if for fear of plundering and undoing, Death and Torment; Hope of keeping our Estates, or getting more; If for these or such like Motives, we shall presume to be false to this Oath, we have just Reason to fear the Judgments of God upon us, who will not <hi>hold him guiltless, who taketh his Name in vain.</hi> There's no limitation in these Oaths of <hi>Allegiance and Supremacy,</hi> no more than there is in the <hi>Protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and for us so to limit, distinguish and subtlelise the Sense of these Oaths, as to make them no further obligatory than they shall make for our present wordly advantage, is contrary to the simplicity of an Oath; is a scandal to our Religion; and (in plain terms) is neither better nor worse, than (as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <hi>Sanderson</hi> expresses it) to <hi>play fast and loose with God
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97880:21"/> himself,</hi> at the same time when we call him to witness the sincerity, truth and singleness of our Intentions.</p>
               <p>God punished the King of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> for breaking the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant he had made with the King of <hi>Babylon, Ezek.</hi> xvii, from <hi>verse</hi> the 12. to the 21. but was the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> therefore absolv'd from his part of the Covenant, so far as it was not expresly conditional, or necessarily so, in its nature? You might here have observ'd, <hi>That this Oath</hi> is <hi>not only</hi> call'd <hi>the King of Babylon</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> but that God himself also calls it, <hi>mine Oath;</hi> but then, you ought to make this serious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, That an Oath taken to a lawful Sovereign is question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less no less the <hi>Oath of God,</hi> no less than this, which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> the Conquering Tyrant. And if God held himself oblig'd to punish the breach of this Oath, will he <hi>hold them guiltless</hi> (think you) who can so easily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense with the Oaths which they have taken to their right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, when no Conquest is pretended? In the Oath which the two Spies swore to <hi>Rhahab,</hi> there was a condition plainly mention'd. <hi>But if thou utter this business, then we will be quit, &amp;c.</hi> Jos. 11.20. Would any one therefore but your self, from this particular, conclude in general—<hi>That the Non-Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of an Oath on one side, makes the other become void?</hi> What reasoning is this? Pray Sir, shew us that you are a Man, at least, of some common Sense, though you be no great Clerk. Your Argument from the Father's ratifying or disan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling the vow of his Daughter; or the Husband's, that of his Wife; seems more proper to the business in hand; but yet, when 'tis nearly examin'd, we shall find it as lame and imperfect, as the rest. Daughters and Wives are immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under the care of their respective Fathers and Husbands, and therefore by their Authority they might confirm or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the vows of their Wives and Daughters; but what is this to an Oath taken by the People to their Prince? Who shall dispense with this Oath? surely none but the Prince or God himself. If the Prince doth not, let any one shew me, that God, by his word, hath absolv'd me, and I will be his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selyte as long as this Oath remains lawful in it self, and possible
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97880:21"/> to be perform'd, so long it certainly binds if any Oath can oblige the Conscience. But if Oaths are but Words,
<q>
                     <l>—And Words are but Wind,</l>
                     <l>Too feeble Instruments to bind;</l>
                  </q> then, I confess, they are in the right of it, who (to save themselves and their Fortunes) resolve to take any Oaths, and keep none. Then— <hi>Jura &amp; Perjura, secretum prodere noli—</hi> is a commendable peice of Prudence; and they who walk by this Rule (or rather no Rule at all) are the only wise Men, whose example we ought to follow. But if this Wisdom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend not from above, but (like the gross Vapors of the Earth) arises from beneath; and is <hi>Earthly, Sensual, Devilish;</hi> then God grant I may never be amongst the number of these <hi>Wise Men,</hi> but rather one of those <hi>foolish and despised things,</hi> who chuse Affliction, rather than Sin; and to be miserable in this World, rather than run the fatal Risque of being so here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>Our next Inquiry is, Whether Protection, be the only Ground and Foundation of Allegiance? You say it is. And your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is, because <hi>the Prince Swears to Govern and Protect the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple according to Law,</hi> &amp;c. So then, <hi>'tis Swearing to Govern and Protect the People according to Law,</hi> that is the Foundation of Allegiance, and not barely his <hi>Protecting and Governing the People according to Law,</hi> if he doth not <hi>Swear</hi> to do so. And thus Allegiance at last, is resolv'd into the <hi>Coronation Oath.</hi> But what if the Prince is willing, when he is not able to Protect his People according to Law, as he has Sworn? What if another, stronger than he, shall come and dethrone him, and (taking the Government into his own hands) shall him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self swear to <hi>Govern according to Law?</hi> Must I obey the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or the later? My rightful Prince, who has Sworn, and is willing but not able to Protect me? Or the other, who has also Sworn, and is (<hi>we'll</hi> suppose) as willing, as he is able to Protect me? Not the former; for his Power is gone, and he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97880:22"/> cannot Protect me, though he has Sworn that he will, and is desirous to keep his Oath. I must therefore, according to your Principles, obey the later; and thus at last the longest Sword carries it, and becomes the <hi>only sure Foundation of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance;</hi> and consequently the King of <hi>France,</hi> as I said (at least if he shall <hi>Swear to Govern according to Law</hi>) ought, if he be the strongest, to be received by all those who make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection the only <hi>Foundation of Allegiance;</hi> so unluckily do some Men form their Arguments (when they design to serve an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest) as to oppose that very interest, which their Arms are at the same time employ'd to support and maintain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 21.) I'm glad to find you so favourable as to grant, <hi>That 'tis not every little violation of the King's, by which the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is absolv'd from the Oath of Allegiance;</hi> but if <hi>the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to overthrow the Government,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They are not</hi> (you say) <hi>bound by this Oath, to stand still, and let him.</hi> But if the Sovereign Authority cannot lawfully be resisted by Force of Arms, they can only perswade, remonstrate, humbly beseech, and intreat him not to follow such evil Councils. And this you know, was done by the great Confessors of the Nation. This Oath, in your judgement, is not to be taken in the literal Sense; and you reckon up the grievous inconveniences, which would thence ensue. Now I confess, I have hitherto thought, That all Oaths are to be taken <hi>in the plain literal and Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sense,</hi> and no other; for this only is the Sense which cuts off all <hi>Aequivocations and mental Reservations whatsoever;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jesuitical, or Puritanical. I must needs tell you, that you do here advance the most <hi>pernicious and damnable Principle,</hi> both in respect of Religion and Civil Society, that ever any Man, since <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> pretended to countenance. If an Oath is not to be taken <hi>in the literal Sense,</hi> then what doth it signifie, Whether I swear to observe and teach the <hi>Articles and Canons of the Church of</hi> England, or those of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent?</hi> Whether I undertake to make the <hi>Bible</hi> or the <hi>Alcoran</hi> the Rule of my Faith? To tell People that an Oath is not to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97880:22"/> be taken in the Literal, but in any Sense whatsoever they shall put upon it, is quite contrary to the Nature and End of an Oath; which is, to cut off all ambiguity, and double dealing with one another. And this can never be, if the Words of an Oath must not be taken in their <hi>plain, common, obvious and Literal Sense.</hi> As for our Baptismal Vow (which you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to debauch, as if it did Authorize your Principle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance) I pray God, that we may all keep that better than hitherto we have done, and then we shall, I doubt not, be less Solicitous, how to find out evasions, whereby we may absolve our selves from the <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Head is so full of Government, and King <hi>James</hi>'s vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it, that the frequent repetitions of these things, do serve you for Answers to every thing; and consequently, to nothing. Here follows a great deal to this purpose; which I shall pass over in silence, as I desire to do hereafter, as often as I shall meet with the same <hi>Crambe repetita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fortune of War in <hi>Flanders</hi> (which you insist upon) comes not up to the present Case. For, our late Revolution, is not a Conquest; neither is it so received, the Title is grounded upon another bottom. <hi>First,</hi> that of the Peoples Election. <hi>The Scripture directs Obedience</hi> (you say) <hi>to the Powers in Being.</hi> You ought to have added, <hi>upon the pain of Damnation.</hi> Now put these two together, and what will hereafter become of them, who were lately so far from obeying <hi>the Power in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, i. e.</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> that they deserted, betray'd and oppos'd him, He was. 'tis evident the <hi>Power in Being,</hi> and whilst he was so, by your own Rule, the Word of God pronounces them disobedient Rebels and Traytors, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sook and delivered him up into the hands of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>Hitherto you have labour'd to prove, That if the King breaks his Coronation Oath, his Subjects are absolv'd from that of Allegiance. You do now give us a word or two, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King's Obligation to observe the Coronation Oath, when his Subjects do not keep that of Allegiance. And to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97880:23"/> what you say, let those return an Answer, who are concern'd. <hi>—If the People endeavour to destroy or kill the King, the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oath neither does nor can bind him to Protect them; but on the contrary, he commits a notorious Sin against the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if he does not defend himself, and destroy them; if there is a necessity for it, to preserve himself.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 22.) My Assertion is, <hi>that the Public would suffer more by the Impunity of bad Subjects, than of evil Kings.</hi> You maintain the contrary. And the reason which you offer is, <hi>because Subjects are punishable for the least Misdemeanors, and the King not.</hi> But if it once be taken for granted, That Kings are punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by their Subjects, the People must judge when 'tis fitting they should be corrected; and to save themselves from being punished for their own faults (whether great or small) they'l, you may be assured, be beforehand with the King, and judge his small Misdemeanors to be great Crimes; and will call him to an account for them, when they are strong enough to set a Guard upon him, and bring him before an High-Court of Justice in <hi>Westminister-Hall.</hi> Then <hi>the Motes</hi> in the King's Eye, shall (through their false Opticks) be magnifyed into <hi>Beams;</hi> and they (not beholding the Beams in their own Eyes) will be very much concern'd to clear the King's Eye-sight.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>King ceases to Govern by Law,</hi> he doth not (as you say) <hi>cease to govern,</hi> but he ceases to govern as he ought to do; but this none (except some of <hi>Corah's</hi> Companions) will say, doth un-king him, and utterly destroy his Regal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. And if this was the Case (supposing the worst) when the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> Landed, the consequence is easie. Your Reply to the 18th and 19th Paragraphs I have already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd, to which you refer me, as if your chief strength lay therein. If it doth, I must tell you, that I am in no appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sions of all the force you can bring against me.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 23.) Here we are agree'd; and the Foundation of our agreement is—<hi>That none are obliged to do any thing that is sinful, though it be commanded by the greatest Potentate upon Earth.</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:97880:23"/> But then I wish we were agreed in another point, which is, that we ought to suffer, rather than Rebel, when the Supream Power commands that which is sinful. These two things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, the matter might be easily accommodated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 24.) I am for perswading Men to perform their Duty, both to God and their Country; but you will needs divide these two, and suppose Men Rebels either to the one or the other. And then you speak, as if (like one of the Jewish Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots) you were appointed by God, to execute Vengeance upon the Rebellious. <hi>How can I be true to my King and Country, if I let Men Rebel against the Laws, by violating them every day?</hi> This is spoken like a Man of Authority, and carries with it such a dominant and decisive Air, as better becomes one of the King's Judges, than any private Man, as I suppose you to be. If you be otherwise, I beg your Pardon.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 25.) But now comes the great Stumbling-block, <hi>Passive Obedience;</hi> which I find gives you such offence, that it puts you out of all patience, and makes you rave like a Man, who together with his Christianity, has also lost his Reason. Your Position is, that <hi>Passive Obedience is Popery Established by Law, and by consequence, slavery, whenever the Prince shall please.</hi> To which my Answer was—<hi>Passive Obedience is neither Popery nor Slavery Establish'd by Law, but the Doctrine of Jesus Christ, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to none but those, who desire to use their Liberty as a Cloak of maliciousness.</hi> This Answer (you say) is not direct. Let's compare it with yours. <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> (you tell us) <hi>is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Establish'd by Law. Passive Obedience</hi> (I say) <hi>is neither Popery nor Slavery Establish'd by Law.</hi> Which directly opposes your Assertion, taking in also the second Part of it; <hi>and by consequence Slavery, whenever the Prince shall please.</hi> I add over and above—<hi>But the Doctrine of Jesus Christ is grievous to none, but those who desire to use their Liberty, as a Cloak of maliciousness.</hi> I shall now (if you please) give you my Sense, in this Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Proposition; <hi>Passive Obedience, is Christianity Establish'd by the Gospel, and by consequence is so far from being Slavery, when
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97880:24"/> ever the Prince shall please, that they who always Act agreeably to this Principle, can never be made Slaves by the most Arbitrary Prince upon Earth.</hi> The Apostles and Primitive Christians, who govern'd themselves according to this Doctrine, were so far from being Slaves, that they were the most Free-men alive, at the same time when their Persecutors were under the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of their impotent Lusts and Passions; the worst sort of Slavery to which a Rational Man can be condemn'd.</p>
               <p>But you'l Answer, That the Slavery which you mean, is that of the outward Man— <hi>First,</hi> the Subjecting our Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Estates to the Arbitrary Pleasure of the Prince. To this I reply, That this sort of Slavery, is falsely charged upon <hi>Passive Obedience;</hi> which is no more the cause of it, than righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness is the cause of Sin, or Vertue of Vice, because sinful and vicious Men may make their advantages both of the one and of the other. <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> is not such a creeping thing as you imagine. It knows how and when to stand up in the Vindication of all goods Laws, and Laudible Customs of the Country, without running into Rebellion for God's sake; or <hi>making Christ to appear the Author of confusion and destruction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Mankind, instead of Justice and Order;</hi> as your words are. <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> sees, and obeys God in every thing; and is ready to vindicate all that's good and just, even with the loss of life and all that's dear to Men in this World; but yet, will never by Violence and Force of Arms, endeavour to right it self against its lawful Sovereign. Such a Subjection as it requires, is every where suppos'd in Scripture, and is agreeable to the Reason of Mankind, not blinded with Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, or the Interest of this World.</p>
               <p>By this Obedience, Christianity was at first propagated, and it must be still maintain'd. When all is done and said; after we have try'd all the ways of preserving our Liberties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after we have kill'd and affrighted one another with Wars and Rumors of Wars; at the last, Passive Obedience rightly understood, will be found to be beyond all Stratagems and Strength; and Prayers and Tears (how much soever despised)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97880:24"/> the strongest Arms of your Church. To cherish this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is not (good Sir) <hi>to degenerate from Nature,</hi> unless it be <hi>corrupted Nature</hi> which you mean; out of which Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> and his Disciples have taken their depraved Principles. This Doctrine neither tends to the destruction of Christianity, nor any Human Society. On the contrary, it elevates and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves Men's Reason; and of Wild and Savage Heathens makes them mild and gentle Christians, <hi>true Disciples and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Innocent, and Holy Jesus, the Prince of Peace.—</hi>To what a degree therefore of Folly and Madness, to give you your own words (but I hope better apply'd) are some Men arrived, who deride and damn a Doctrine, which is peculiar to Christianity; and absolutely necessary for the support of the truly Ancient, Catholick and Apostolick Religion; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all the Persecutions of <hi>wicked and unreasonable Men;</hi> of what denomination soever?</p>
               <p>I could easily recriminate and charge <hi>Popery and Slavery</hi> too, upon some of our late Proceedings; though the cry was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether against these two Companions. But 'tis well known, that (the People of <hi>England</hi> having such an irreconcilable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to these two Enemies of Religion and Liberty) the only way to introduce them, is loudly and bitterly to exclaim against, whilst at the same time, all Arts are used to Establish them, under some popular and specious Pretences. But I shall not here draw this Parallel at length; only give me leave to say, that if <hi>Odelschalchi</hi> himself, the late Pope, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted, and the measures of the <hi>Vatican</hi> were followed in the late <hi>Revolution;</hi> this is no very great sign, methinks, that the Interest of <hi>Popery</hi> is not at the bottom: And if the <hi>Dutch</hi> Scheme and Methods of Policy, must be the Standard and Platform of our Government (as 'tis very likely they must in most things, except the name of King) 'tis very probable, that, how much soever we may <hi>promise Liberty to our selves,</hi> we shall, at last, see our selves reduc'd to as great Slavery as the poor People are in <hi>Holland;</hi> where (if we will believe the learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> who had reason to know the State of that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97880:25"/> Country) <hi>there remains nothing but the name of Liberty. Cum videam</hi> (says he in his <hi>Epistle</hi> 298. written to <hi>Ger. Vossius) apud vos, ubi tantum pro Libertate depensum est, vix quicquam ejus praeter nomen restare.</hi> Grot. Epist. fol. 108. But, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Section; This Doctrine of Passive Obedience ('tis true) as all that is good, may be abused. And I question not, but Men of Intrigue have endeavour'd to bring about their own bad Designs, by the means thereof. But, if the abuse of any thing is a sufficient Argument against it, the Sun it self, ought to be removed out of the Firmament; because Evil Men use the Light thereof, in the perpetration of the <hi>Works of Darkness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 26.) What Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did in reference to the <hi>French</hi> Protestants and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> let the Statesmen answer for. I am no competent Judge in the case. I do not take upon me to dive into the Reasons of State, or determine concerning the Actions of Independent Princes, towards one another. If this great Patroness both of Law and Religion did deviate something from her usual measures in this Affair, it may serve to put us in mind, that the best of Governours and of Princes are but too apt sometimes to follow their Interest ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than their Duty. Her Answer to the <hi>French</hi> Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, in the Case of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> was, I'm sure, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Nature. <hi>Abdicandi principes exemplum, perniciosum est, &amp; infrà inferos damnandum. The Example of abdicating Princes is indeed pernicious; and ought to be condemn'd to the Pit of Hell.</hi> Cambd. Eliz. Lat. fol. 223.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 27.) You have (you say) <hi>as honourary a respect for a King as any Man whatsoever, whilst he continues his Kingly Office (i. e.</hi> whilst he pleases you) <hi>but when he shall degenerate and break all his sacred Oaths; (i. e.</hi> when he doth not Rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your liking) <hi>then you have</hi> (i. e. you think you have) <hi>Reason to turn your Love into Contempt.</hi> Though all be true that you have said of King <hi>James,</hi> yet you have reviled the <hi>Lord's anointed.</hi> For who gave you Commission to tell him of Faults, and maliciously to publish such stuff to the World?
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97880:25"/>
'Tis neither decent, nor dutiful for a Private Person to lay open the failures and miscarriages of his Prince; and take all occasions (as you do in every Paragraph, and almost in every line of this Pamphlet) to expose him as a Person not only unfit to govern, but to live. This intemperate Zeal of yours, what popular Cloak soever you shall throw over it, to me appears to be nothing else, but <hi>Reviling your King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To your Question, <hi>what Right hath the King to the Throne, but from the People?</hi> I will answer, when you can shew me, that the People ever had any Right at all to make Kings. In the mean time to your Question I shall only oppose this. What Right have the People (especially of <hi>England</hi>) to Judge, Condemn and Depose one Prince, and set up another? What ever becomes of the <hi>Jure-Divino</hi> Doctrine (which we shall speak of afterwards) the successive Hereditary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>England,</hi> is establish'd by Law, and you'l grant, I hope, that 'tis <hi>Jure-Divino,</hi> to maintain the <hi>lawful Constitution</hi> of every Nation.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 28.) That God did command or appoint his own People the <hi>Jews</hi> to be govern'd by Monarchs all along, (tho they were not always call'd Kings) I do find by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; That, he ever revoked that Form of Government, I do not read. Yet, I will not, I tell you, maintain, that all other Governments are sinful. If you be resolv'd to prove this (as you say you will, <hi>p.</hi> 31.) pray do you undertake the Province; and shew us—<hi>That the Government by Kings is necessary, and that all others are sinful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> 29, 30.) I beg leave, Sir, to ask you where you have lived, that you <hi>never till now heard that a Paternal (i. e.</hi> A Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Authority as you critically observe) <hi>is a Kingly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> Our Education, it seems, has been very different. For I scarce ever heard otherwise, but from those who would have all Kings to be so many <hi>Nimrods;</hi> not Fathers, but Robbers and Spoylers of their Country.</p>
               <p>Why may it not be said, that <hi>Adam</hi> was a King, as to his Power and the Exercise of it, when besides the <hi>Dominion</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97880:26"/> given to him over the Fish of the Sea, the Fowls of the Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he had (as you grant) <hi>Power and Authority over his Children, to subdue them, if Rebellious in disobeying his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands?</hi> What Power and Authority has any King greater than this? If he had <hi>Dominion</hi> over all Creatures, and <hi>Empire</hi> over all his numerous Family, you cannot reasonably deny, that (considering how long he lived, which was until about 620 Years of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood, for the Deluge happened after the Creation about the Year, 1656. And <hi>Adam</hi> lived 930 Years; so by a moderate Computation we may allow him to be a Monarch over some Millions of People) that he was the first, and none of the meanest Monarchs of the World. As for the name of King, I will not contend with you about the Word, if you yield the thing it self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Twelve Sons of</hi> Jacob, <hi>after the Flood</hi> (you agree) <hi>were Chief Fathers, and Chief-Head Princes of their Families: and such</hi> (as you go on to argue for me, as well as I could wish) <hi>was</hi> Abraham <hi>who was called a Father (not King) of many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</hi> All this confirms my Notion. For a Father of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is a King in my Sense of the Word. And consequently, the Patriarchs (being chief Fathers of Families and Countries where they lived) were, in effect so many Kings. And <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (being a Father of many Countries) was perhaps one of the most Potent Kings, at that time, in the World. Thus, during the time of the Patriarchs, there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, but about the name. And this <hi>Scripture-Notion of Kingly and Paternal Power being the same, Aristotle</hi> himself (though no great Friend to Monarchies) had learn'd; when (convinc'd either by the Reason of the Thing or the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of these Holy Writings) he tells us—<hi>That Regal Power belonged to the Father of the Family,</hi> Polit. Lib. 1. Cap. 8.</p>
               <p>We now pass on to the time of the <hi>Judges.</hi> And they (you say) <hi>were not Monarchs, for the time being, but Rulers over the People.</hi> Now that Judges were <hi>Rulers of the People, for the time being,</hi> is very true; but it doth by no means follow,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97880:26"/> that, therefore they were not <hi>Monarchs.</hi> For, 'tis evident that they were single Rulers, that is, so many Monarchs or Kings <hi>for time being.</hi> As for the Text which you quote upon this occasion, you might as well have referr'd us to any Text in the whole Bible, wherein the word <hi>(Rulers)</hi> is to be found. The words are—<hi>Then</hi> Peter, <hi>full of the Holy Ghost, said unto them, ye Rulers of the People, and Elders of</hi> Israel, &amp;c. Do you fancy, these Rulers, unto whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress'd himself, to have been of the same Nature with those, who were made Judges of <hi>Israel,</hi> after <hi>Joshua</hi>'s time? If you do, I pitty your Ignorance. 'Tis such a mistake as must needs spoil your Credit, with all your Readers, even those of the meanest Capacity; for whom you seem to write. After such an escape as this, for shame, never pretend to set up for an <hi>Expositor of Scripture,</hi> and throw out such foolish Challenges against those, who, I assure you, do better understand these <hi>Sacred Writings,</hi> and have more Veneration for them, than to abuse and pervert them so miserably as you have done here and in other Places.</p>
               <p>But to go on with you; you allow that <hi>Melchisedeck</hi> and <hi>Moses,</hi> are said, in Scripture, to have been Kings, and that God also owned <hi>Cyrus</hi> for his <hi>anointed;</hi> but <hi>Melchisedeck was a Type of Christ;</hi> Moses <hi>a very Holy Man;</hi> Cyrus <hi>made a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to Build the House of God;</hi> and therefore these Persons (you say) were particularly honoured with these Titles. <hi>It may, with Reason, be concluded, that God gave him an Honour above other Prophets, by making him a King</hi> (say you of <hi>Moses.</hi>) Now, since you grant the Title of a King to be an Honour, I hope, in time, you may be reconcil'd unto the Office; and not derive all Kings from <hi>Nimrod,</hi> who seems to have been recorded rather as a Tyrant, than a King; and may be the first Example of a wicked Prince, not the first Monarch, we meet with in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The Judges and Officers, which the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were commanded to make, throughout their Tribes (in Number 12, as you learnedly observe, and lest we should not believe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97880:27"/> you, cite two Texts for it, <hi>Gen.</hi> xlix. 28. <hi>Mat.</hi> xix. 28.) These Judges and Officers, were all, at the time of their first institution, under <hi>Moses;</hi> and you known the end of some of these <hi>Men of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown,</hi> who rose up in Rebellion against him, who, at that time, was <hi>King in Jeshurun.</hi> And in after times these Judges and Officers, were all under the Kings of <hi>Israel;</hi> as our Judges and Officers are under the Kings of <hi>England.</hi> They were a sort of Magistrates, as much different from those Judges, who, in times of eminent danger, were chosen for <hi>Israel</hi>'s Deliverance; as the Pretors and other Officers, were from the <hi>Roman</hi> Dictators, who were made upon extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary occasions, and had the Power of the the Sword committed to them <hi>for the time being.</hi> And so the Judges of <hi>Israel</hi> had Kingly Power, whilst God pleased to continue them in their Office; and though they are sometimes said to have been chosen by the People, yet in truth, they were always <hi>raised up, and chosen</hi> before by God himself, as <hi>Gideon</hi> was. <hi>Judges</hi> iv. 12, 13, 14. And so, this makes nothing at all, against the <hi>Jure Divino Doctrine;</hi> which yet, together with that of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> you grant, did obtain <hi>during the time of the Children of Israel.</hi> p. 35.</p>
               <p>This concession I cannot let pass without some Observations upon it; though I profess I am quite tired with examining your bold Assertions; when you bring neither Wit, nor Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor Scripture (which you pretend to the most and know the least) to support them. <hi>Passive Obedience and Jure Divino, used</hi> (you say) <hi>to go together, during the time of the Children of Israel.</hi> Very good! Then the Old Testament is on our sides; and these Doctrines (you yield) were once approved by God himself, and delivered by him to his own peculiar People. If this be so, I desire you to shew, that the New Testament has altered the Case, and parted these two inseparable companions in the time of the Jewish-State; or else <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Jure Divino</hi> are still in force against you. Now, that the New Testament has made no alteration as to these things, I thus argue—Our Saviour strictly enjoyns
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97880:27"/> us to render unto <hi>Caesar,</hi> the things that are <hi>Caesar</hi>'s. <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> did by your own Confession, belong unto Kings, <hi>during the time of the Children of Israel; i. e.</hi> till the time of Gospel.</p>
               <p>Therefore I conclude, that the <hi>Rights of Caesar are from God;</hi> and that we ought, <hi>for the Lord's sake, passively to submit</hi> to his commands, when we cannot <hi>actively obey</hi> them. And thus we are both by the Law and the Gospel bound to govern our selves by these Doctrins. To say, That what was true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>King's of Israel,</hi> is not so, when apply'd to the <hi>Kings of the Nations,</hi> will do you no service. For <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> from his time, were (as the People desired) Kings, <hi>after the manner of the Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to insist no further upon this, I go on; and must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand satisfaction of you for your scurrilous and prophane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, which you bestow upon those Doctrins, which you acknowledge, went together, <hi>during the time of the Children of Israel.</hi> To quote the Scriptures, for them, is (you say) to <hi>wrest them;</hi> when the Scriptures especially the Old Testament, every where (you confess) doth suppose them. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>They are Doctrins, which inevitably tend to the destruction of Christianity, and to all human Societies;</hi> p. 26. <hi>not fit for Savage Heathens, much less for rational Men.</hi> ib. Those who assert them, <hi>fit to be compared to Papists.</hi> ib. They are <hi>inhuman and damnable Principles.</hi> p. 37. Now, as for mine own part, I can easily pass by and forgive all these hard words, were I, or any particular Doctrins of mine own broaching only concern'd therein; but when these false accusations, and lew'd <hi>Epithites</hi> do reach the Scripture it self, and reflect upon God's own Institutions, <hi>during the time of the Children of Israel,</hi> (by your own account) what can you say for your self? What amends can you make for the injury you have done to the <hi>word of God,</hi> and for the scandal which you have given to Religion, and all good Men? What reparation can you make, but by acknowledging your Crime, and your serious repentance for it? And how can your Repentance be so, if your Retractation be not as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97880:28"/> public, as the injury you have done to Religion; and the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front you have given to the Bible, and consequently to God himself, whose <hi>Word</hi> it is?</p>
               <p>And as for the Doctrine of <hi>Non-resistance</hi> in particular, even the present Government it self is concern'd, to call you to an account, for what you have said about it. For, all it's true and real strength stands upon this bottom; and not upon the Principle of Fear, which is Tyrannical; and makes no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciencious impression upon Men's minds. <hi>If a Man does not obey for Conscience sake</hi> (as 'tis certain they do not who maintain the lawfulness of Rebellion in any Case) <hi>all the Cords of outward Pacts and Covenants will not hold him, when he Dreams that the</hi> Philistines <hi>are upon him, and he can deliver himself by Force, from the Power of his Enemies; as</hi> Dr. <hi>Tennison</hi> (in his <hi>Hobs</hi>'s <hi>Creed</hi>) assures us. <hi>This is no more than the Loyalty of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan;</hi> says Mr. <hi>Pelling (Serm. Jan.</hi> 30. — 83. <hi>p.</hi> 43.) How necessary soever the Doctrine of <hi>Resistance,</hi> sometimes may be thought to be in bringing Men to the top of Empire and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; that of <hi>Non-resistance</hi> will always be necessary to keep them in Possession. Accordingly I perceive, that this Doctrine is now likely to have it's <hi>Habeas Corpus;</hi> and be discharged from all those horrible Indictments, which by you and others of your Spirit, have been brought against it. For I find, by the Title of a Late Pamphlet, 'tis now the opinion, that <hi>this Doctrine is not concern'd in the Controversie betwixt the</hi> Williamites <hi>and the</hi> Jacobites; (as some learned <hi>Monk</hi> has taught them to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish.) So that you see, Sir, one of your Points is drop't, and given up (as I may suppose) by Authority. For, we have notice of this Phamphlet, <hi>in the Continuation of the Proceedings in</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, N. 58. <hi>Licensed and Entered according to Order.</hi> And as for the other thing which so much offends you, the <hi>Jure Divino Doctrine,</hi> it follows of course. For if it be in no Case lawful to rise in Arms against our Sovereign Prince, 'tis a sure sign that his Character is more than human; and consequently, that it is in truth, Divine. And thus your quarrel is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, even in the Judgment of those, whom you pretend to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97880:28"/> serve; and the Doctrins which you so furiously damn, and which have provok'd you to make this unaccountable Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, are receiv'd into favour, or at least, begin to be look'd upon as innocent By-standers, not concern'd in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie. And truly, the present Government, let me tell you, has as little Reason to suspect these Principles, as it has to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage such a dubious and ill qualify'd Advocate for it, as you appear to be. All that you say, may be turn'd against one King as well as another; when your present Favourite shall displease you, or his good success shall fail him. And surely those useless <hi>Harangues</hi> ought to be despised by all sides, which do really serve none at all; and every Government, which bears the name of Kingly, ought to be jealous of one, who Advances such Opinions, as do equally strike at all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of that Denomination. I could easily present the Reader with a cast of your Loyal Sayings, which are Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonous in the Eye of our Law, and have been often so adjudged when time shall serve, which side soever shall, at last prevail. So that, probably, you may live to make your own Recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ask Pardon for your Republican Propositions and Assertions; instead of glorying in them, and undertaking to defend them, with your Learned Pen.</p>
               <p>Thus, Sir, I have (according to your direction) examin'd this Paragraph; whether <hi>well</hi> or not, neither you nor I are to judge, but the honest and impartial Reader. This, I think, I may confidently say, that I have not <hi>wrested any Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (as you charge me) neither have I, I hope, <hi>made any false assertion.</hi> This (as I remember) is the third time you have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd me for <hi>wresting the Scriptures.</hi> I do Challenge you to prove your Allegation, or else you must pass for a <hi>false Accuser of your Brethren,</hi> and you know, to whom that Character be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs.</p>
               <p>As to your demand of proving Kings to be <hi>by the Command and Appointment of God Almighty;</hi> because you are importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, I shall at present lay down these things, which I shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon, as you shall give occasion. <hi>First,</hi> That <hi>de facto,</hi> God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97880:29"/> hath <hi>commanded and appointed</hi> Kingly Government in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and no other that I know of. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Kingly or Monarchical Government is absolutely the best in it self. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That in <hi>England</hi> particularly, is an Hereditary Monarchy; and ought to devolve successively upon the next of the Royal Line. When you shall think fit to shew your skill, by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing these Assertions, I shall, according to my small Abilities, endeavour to defend them. But let me Advise you to be more Methodical and Argumentative than hitherto you have been, or else I shall loose no more time upon you; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that your Talent lies rather in Dictating <hi>Political Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rismes,</hi> than proving them by the Force and Evidence of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; and that, you'r resolv'd to hold fast your Conclusions, whatever shall become of the poor Premises, which ought to support them.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 31.) You here repeated over again, what you said <hi>N.</hi> 20. and 21. and which I have in these places already considered. I am not at leasure to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke notice of your impertinent Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as often as you sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l think fit to make them.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 32.) As for the Law concerning an Usurper, or <hi>de facto</hi> King, 'tis the only appearance of Law, that you have on your side; which yet, if it be throughly scan'd, doth not in the least countenance, much less altogether excuse our late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. There are many things to be said concerning this Law, which the brevity of this discourse will not permit. I shall therefore breifly propose some things, which may be more fully insisted upon hereafter. As <hi>First,</hi> It cannot be reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably supposed, that this Law doth Establish any such Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as they would draw from it, who produce it as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answerable Authority against all objections. The Principle, which our late States-men would draw from this Act, is, <hi>That, Possession of the Throne, without any other Right, is a sufficient Title?</hi> King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. needed no such Principle, and therefore 'tis not probable, that the Parliament by which it was enacted, did intend to encourage any such Doctrine. Or, if it did, can it be thought that the ensuing Parliaments, would have left it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97880:29"/> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repeal'd all this time? In truth this Opinion—That <hi>Possession, without any other right, is a sufficient Title,</hi> is founded only upon Sr. <hi>Edward Cook's</hi> Authority, who first maintain'd. That a King <hi>de facto</hi> only, is <hi>Seigneur Le Roy within the purvein of the Statute of</hi> 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Now Sr. <hi>Edw. C.</hi> though he was a great Lawyer, yet has been, 'tis very well known, remarkably famous for corrupting the Law, as much as ever any one, of his Profession, ever did. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Supposing, that this 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. did really intend to make Possession a sure Title, yet it cannot now be pleaded, because 'tis vertually repealed by the first of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> by which Statute we are oblig'd to Swear to be true to the <hi>Queen, her Heirs and lawful Successors,</hi> that is, those who have a Right to the Crown, by proximity of Blood. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Supposing that this Statute is in Force at present, yet will not it be serviceable to those who desire to shelter themselves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its Protection. For 'tis provided in this Act—<hi>That no Person shall take benefit and advantage by this Act, which shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after decline from his or their said Allegiance.</hi> This is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso of this Statute, upon which a very learned Person (whose Treatise I have by me, and out of which I must confess, I have had most of these hints) thus argues. <q>If Allegiance by this Act be due to a King <hi>de facto,</hi> then certainly (by the same Act) 'tis equally due to him, who is a King <hi>de facto</hi> and <hi>de jure</hi> too. Therefore those who decline from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to a King <hi>de jure,</hi> are expressly bar'd from receiving any benefit by this Act. So that, now they must lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lash of all those Antecedent Laws, which punish all Disloyal Practises against a rightful King, whether in, or out, of Possession.</q> Thus doth this judicious Person reason upon this Act. And accordingly 'tis certain, that (notwithstanding this Act) by several Acts in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 4th, the <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys</hi> were declared <hi>Ʋsurpers,</hi> and that during their Usurpations, the Ancestors of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th were rightful Kings; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently all those, who were then alive, and did decline from their Allegiance to the House of <hi>York</hi> (the Right Line) to the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> (the Kings <hi>de facto</hi>) might have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97880:30"/> as Traytors, and precluded from having any benefit from this Statute. Notwithstanding therefore, any thing that you have said, or any other I have ever discours'd or read upon <hi>this Subject,</hi> the Oath of Allegiance to our King <hi>de jure</hi> still remains <hi>in full</hi> Force and Vertue, not only in point of Conscience, but of Law too.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 33.) The Query is, Whether it <hi>he for the Safety of the People, to violate the Rights of Succession?</hi> To have given a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Answer, you should have shewn, That the good which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends this violation, is greater than the evil which may be feared from it. But instead of this, you run immediately to the Divine Law; and fall upon asking questions, which I am no more bound to Answer, than you are Authorized to propose. You ask, <hi>whether the</hi> Salique Law <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>and the deposing the King of</hi> Portugal <hi>he according to this Law? And whether or no</hi> England <hi>for its security, may not exclude the next Heir to the Crown, or turn out he</hi> (him you mean) <hi>that shall be upon the Throne, who are</hi> (is you should have said) <hi>uncapable, or will not govern according to the Laws of the Land?</hi> I am no ways oblig'd to resolve these doubts, before it be decided, Whether to <hi>violate the Right of Succession</hi> (especially where it is Establish'd by Law) <hi>be for the Safety of the People?</hi> If this be once determin'd all your Queries will be easily solved; which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise cannot be Answered without Ambiguity. But because I love not to be uncivil, and because the <hi>Safety of the People,</hi> rightly understood, doth never clash with the <hi>Divine Law;</hi> what if I shall give you this general Answer, which both confirms my Opinion (<hi>i. e. that it is not for the Safety of the People to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> &amp;c.) and satisfies your Demands, in reference to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis most beneficial to the public, and most according to the <hi>Divine Law,</hi> that all Monarchies should be Hereditary and Successive; But yet this doth not hinder, but that some particular exceptions, might be lawfully made, by the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a Nation, when the manner of the Succession was at
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97880:30"/> first agree'd upon. Such an exception is the <hi>Salique Law;</hi> but in <hi>England,</hi> we have no such exceptions agreed upon by King and People. As for your Instances in 18. and 19. Replies, I have already accounted for them. I confess I never have been so happy as to have seen the <hi>Fundamental Contract</hi> of the Nation, by which the People are Authorized to depose their <hi>King; upon pretence that he is uncapable, or will not govern according to Law;</hi> If you have it by you, and out of it can shew me that our Ancestors did (by vertue of this Charter) <hi>make King's and turn them out as they pleas'd;</hi> you will much oblige me by a sight of it. Till then, I must own, that I think it <hi>no es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say</hi> (as you elegantly express it) <hi>upon our Reason,</hi> and that they were neither <hi>Fools nor Madmen,</hi> not to reserve to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves such a Power. As for the business of <hi>Portugal,</hi> I am not so well vers'd in the Laws and Customs of that Nation, as to pronounce any thing about it.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 24.) Here you insert the later part of your 29. Query, because, I was, it seems, so forgetful as not to take any notice of it in its proper place. I do assure you, Sir, this Omission was not because I thought it unanswerable, but rather because it deserved no Answer; and yet is treated as it deserves else where: For you have repeated it more than once. However, because 'tis your Herculean Argument, and the very <hi>Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of your Cause, I shall here again consider it. <hi>If Kings are by Divine Appointment, is it not rational to believe that God would have commanded all the World to have been govern'd by Kings, or at least the Christian World, and have given them a Law to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern by?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you; to which I Answer—<hi>That Kings, whether they come to their Thrones by Inheritance, Donation, Conquest, or even Election it self, are by Divine appointment,</hi> I do not think; <hi>That God should therefore have appointed all the World to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by Kings, or at least, the Christian World,</hi> by an express Law, <hi>is not rational to believe,</hi> unless it be <hi>rational</hi> to prescribe to God Almighty, and tell him what he shall do. Yet 'tis
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97880:31"/>
                  <hi>rational to believe,</hi> that this is the Government which he most approves; because we do not find that ever he erected any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Form of Civil Government but this; or, that we are commanded to pray for any other sort of Governors, <hi>but Kings and all in Authority under them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Episcopacy</hi> is by <hi>Divine Appointment</hi> or <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> Yet where do we find that God hath, in express Terms, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the World to be govern'd by Bishops? Yet the Constant and Universal Practice of the Church, hath recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended this Government as the best, and most <hi>agreeable to the Will of God.</hi> And thus the Authority and Universality of Kingly Government, do argue that it has been received by all Countries and Nations, as most agreeable to the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and consequently to the mind of him, who is the <hi>Author of Nature. Principio</hi> (says <hi>Justin</hi> in his History) <hi>rerum, gentium, nationumque imperium penes Reges erat. The Rule of all things, Countries and Nations, were in the hands of Kings, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By what follows it appears, that you are only for a King of your own making. The Reason is, that you make and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make him again when you please. For, if <hi>the King for the time being,</hi> exceeds his bounds, <hi>then most certainly, the People who gave him his Authority, has Authority to take it away;</hi> so that your King is only a King <hi>durante populi beneplacito,</hi> and <hi>quamdiu bene gesserit.</hi> It concerns him therefore to look to himself, and beware of his pretended Friends, as much, if not more, than those, whom he may account his Enemies. For the People, who are his Judges, are very hard to please, and seldom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long in one mind. They are partial and passionate Judges; and will soon Pronounce him Guilty and cast him off, as a <hi>Person not fit to govern,</hi> if he will not humour them in all their lawless and extravagant demands. And thus <hi>Kings for the time being</hi> (seeing they are only <hi>Tenants at Will to the People</hi>) are likely to have but a short, and probably, no very merry Reign of it.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97880:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What a perilous thing were it to commit to Subjects the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which Prince is Wise and Godly, and his Government good, and which otherwise? As though the Foot must Judge of the Head; an Enterprize very heinous, and which must needs breed Rebellion.</hi> Thus our excellent <hi>Hom.</hi> against Rebellion (<hi>part.</hi> 1.)</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 35.) <hi>That the</hi> Roman <hi>Emperors did seldom Succeed by an Hereditary Right; and that the Primitive Christians were not bound to them by Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, you grant.</hi> Yet, <hi>the Commands</hi> (you say) <hi>of our Saviour and his Apostles for their Obedience—under pain of Damnation, were more binding, than any Oath those Princes could have required of them.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore <hi>à Fortiori;</hi> That, if the Primitive Christians thought themselves so strictly oblig'd to Obedience, by the Commands of our Saviour and his Apostles, when they had taken no Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and when the Empire was not Hereditary; That, if their case had been ours (who have taken these Oaths, and live under an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Monarchy) they would have thought themselves to have been <hi>doubly and tribly</hi> bound to have been <hi>subject to the higher Powers.</hi> They would doubtless, if possible, have been more Faithful and Loyal to the Emperor than they were: And if any one should have illegally usurp'd the Empire, they, I'm fully perswaded, would (as we do) have judged it a thing utterly out of their Power, to have absolv'd themselves from these Oaths; and consequently, that they could not in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, have taken any new Oaths which should have been imposed, contrary to their former most solemn Obligations. In short, they would to the last have asserted (as they had sworn) the just <hi>Rights of the Emperors, his Heirs and lawful Successors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 36.) You <hi>ask, Why I undertake to prove the Doctrine of Passive-Obedience, and do not joyn Jure-Divino to it?</hi> Truly, Sir, for any opposition that you can make, I may undertake
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97880:32"/> to prove any thing. I have indeed undertaken to prove the <hi>Doctrine of Passive Obedience;</hi> and, if it will oblige you, I will also make good that of <hi>Jure-Divino,</hi> as I understand it; not <hi>in your Sense;</hi> as I told you before. For you think, that this Doctrine cannot be true, unless all those who are not under a Monarchical Government, be in a <hi>damnable State.</hi> This, I tell you once more, is no true consequence, and I do not undertake for it; how <hi>inhuman and damnable</hi> soever you may think my <hi>Principles</hi> to be.</p>
               <p>You allow, <hi>That during the time of the Children of</hi> Israel (as I have observ'd before) <hi>when God did set up Kings, that</hi> Passive-Obedience <hi>and</hi> Jure-Divino <hi>went together; but now</hi> ('tis your Opinion) <hi>they have ceased.</hi> Why so, I beseech you? Were they only Typical and Figurative Observances? Were they some of those weak and beggarly Elements, from which the Gospel hath emancipated, and set us free? Shew this, or else they still remain Obligatory to you and me and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; as well as formerly to the <hi>Jews</hi> (as I have remarked above.) If you say, that the <hi>Jewish</hi> Kings were of God's appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ours are not; and that therefore these Doctrines cease to oblige, I utterly deny your Antecedent; and do maintain, That our Kings are as well of God's setting up as the <hi>Jewish</hi> were of Old. For by God's Appointment Kings succeeded one another, by an Hereditary Right; except when he pleas'd, by some particular Revelation, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand otherwise. <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi> is a Text applicable to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as it was to those of <hi>Israel;</hi> that is, they instruct us, that all lawful Kings do Reign, not only by Divine Permission (as you pervert these words) but Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; as all good Expositors understand them. At the first, you must grant, that Kings were made by God himself; and where, and when, I desire to be inform'd, hath he assign'd this Power over to the People? Not surely, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against <hi>Moses</hi> and against <hi>Aaron;</hi> no, nor when <hi>Saul</hi> had <hi>broken his Coronation-Oath</hi> with a Witness; <hi>and ceased to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97880:32"/> govern according to the best Law, that ever any People lived under.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Contrarieties</hi> which you desire <hi>me or any Man else to reconcile,</hi> I wish that I may never be put upon an harder task; for then, I shall never need to call any <hi>other Man</hi> to my Assistance. Is it a <hi>contrariety</hi> to say, that he who <hi>resists, (i. e.</hi> By force of Arms) <hi>doth not only resist the Ʋsurpations of Men, but the Ordinance of God, though the Person be a</hi> Claudius <hi>or</hi> Nero: <hi>And that Absolute and Ʋnconditionate Obedience is due only to God, and to the King no otherwise, than as he is his Vicegerent:</hi> Are these things inconsistent, with that <hi>averseness, which I profess to have from having my Throat cut either by</hi> French <hi>or</hi> Irish <hi>Dragoons?</hi> You, who advance the Principle of Self-preservation above all Laws Divine and Humane; will you not suffer me, to be so far <hi>influenc'd by it,</hi> as to have some Reluctances of Flesh and Blood, and to avoid Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if I may honestly do it) when yet rather than resist the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> I'm willing meekly to submit to any Punishment? But when I said, <hi>I am and shall be as averse as you from having my Throat cut,</hi> &amp;c. You thought, I'l warrant you, that my meaning was—I am and shall be as forward to handle my Weapon, and resist by force of Arms, as your self. You much mistake, if you understand me in this Sense. And so your supposed <hi>Contrariety</hi> vanishes into nothing. But I have said more than enough upon this occasion; having already, in the beginning of this Answer, clear'd my self from this Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; as also that of being a <hi>notorious Hypocrite</hi> as your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Sincerity</hi> is pleased kindly to salute me. I will not recriminate; yet let me Counsel you for the future, to be more modest in your personal Reflections; if you intend, that you and I shall have any further Discourse upon these Points.</p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 37.) And now, Sir, as for my Conversation (which you do Hypothetically accuse) it has, I hope, been <hi>agreeable to my Sentiments;</hi> and my Prayer is, that it may ever so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97880:33"/> They that know me can, and many I question not, will (if there was occasion for it) testify, that I have always even in the worst of times, freely declar'd my self against all Rebellious and Schismatical Practices. And, I am so far from being asham'd of what I have done, that I shall, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all discouragements, still endeavour, by the Grace of God to approve my self a Loyal Subject, and an Obedient Son of the Church of <hi>England; however</hi> she shall be <hi>distress'd,</hi> or <hi>wheresoever dispers'd.</hi> 'Tis my Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy to the Monarchy and Church of <hi>England,</hi> which moved me to bestow a few Remarks upon your Paper; which is so destructive both to the one and the other. And, tho now, Ruine and Destruction seem to threaten both; yet, I doubt not, if our Sins do not prevent (which God forbid) but that we, once more, shall see the time, when our Holy Mother shall appear from behind the Cloud, in her former Lustre, and Majestic Simplicity: When those her otherwise Pious and Learned Sons, who, I hope, have rather suspended, than quite abjur'd their Duty, shall return into her Bosom: when renouncing all Rebellion, Heresy and Schism, we shall all, as usually, <hi>go into the House of God as Friends; and with one Heart and one Mind glorify him, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi>N.</hi> 38.) And now I have almost done with my Author; and should indeed here conclude; but that he would account me rude, or something worse, if I should make no return to his Challenge; which here he sends me and all other Men, who still persist in these <hi>inhuman and damnable Principles;</hi> that is, to all <hi>Passive-Obedience and Jure-Divino Men in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>nay in the whole World,</hi> as the direction is more civilly worded in his first Paper.</p>
               <p>Really, Sir, you have acquitted your self with so little Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the management of your <hi>first</hi> Challange, that neither I, nor any one else, can expect to gain any Credit, by accepting your <hi>second.</hi> Yet that, if possible, you may
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97880:33"/> be brought to know your self, and your <hi>Hogan Mogan</hi> Courage may be a little humbled; I have, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Seconds, ventur'd, you see, to enter once more with you, into the Lists; for, to what purpose should I (as you advise) <hi>consult with others,</hi> when I have such an easie Adversary to deal withal? Two (they say) are too many for <hi>Hercules</hi> himself; I'm sure one is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-match for a Man of your Skill and Conduct. And Pardon me, Sir! if (as mean Opinion as I have of my self,) I am encouraged, by the advantage of my Cause, to ingage with such a <hi>Goliah</hi> in Controversy as your self.</p>
               <p>Your bold Challenges and small Performances brings to my Mind the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb; which I think may not be improperly apply'd to your self,
<q>
                     <l>—un altro Orlando,</l>
                     <l>Non con fatti, ma parlando,</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>In Truth, you're just another <hi>Orlando;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not in Deeds, but saying what you can do.</l>
                  </q> You talk a <hi>La Cavaliere,</hi> and as if no body could stand before you; when your performance is so mean, that there's not a <hi>Passive-Obedience or Jure-Divino-Man in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> no nor I believe in <hi>the whole World,</hi> but will easily make his part good with you, and baffle your ill-guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Propositions. I profess my self one of the meanest of them; yet appoint your place, and fit your Weapons; I am once more at your Service, to dispute the Truth of these Doctrines with you.</p>
               <p>But, if you shall think fit to appear again, let me coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel you to take more care of your <hi>English,</hi> than to offend
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97880:34"/> against the common Rules of Grammar; to avoid Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions as much as may be (for I'm sensible that all that you and I have said, abating these Tautologies, may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in a much less room;) to be more clear and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct in your Reasonings, and more consistent with your self; not to accuse me for wresting the Scriptures, when your self do so very much abuse these Sacred Writings: Lastly, abstain (if I may obtain that favour of you) from fixing odious Names and Characters, upon Things or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; unless you shall be very well assured, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve them. Let your Arguments be as hard as Rocks; but let modesty and ingenuity direct and accompany your Words.</p>
               <p>And thus you have both my Answer and Advice. If the one doth not satisfy you; it's your own concern more than mine, to follow the other. But if you shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject both the one and the other; I have only lost so much time upon you, though I hope, others, may reap some little benefit from what hath been said. I profess, had I found any thing in this Answer of yours, to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd me that these Principles are <hi>erroneous</hi> and <hi>damnable,</hi> I should have here publickly recanted them; for I desire willingly to Sacrifice my Reputation to the Interest of <hi>Truth,</hi> and our <hi>Common Salvation.</hi> But being fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in these Doctrines (and more by the weakness of your Objections) I resolve, by the Grace of God, to be true to the Convictions of mine own Mind, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by any mean, sneaking and unlawful Compliances, to renounce those Principles, which are founded upon Reason, Law and Scripture; as they have been defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not only with the Tongues and Pens; but the Blood and Lives of the wisest Men, and best Christians in all Ages of the Church. And particularly, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> has always, ever since the dawning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, defended these Doctrines with all Christian
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97880:34"/> Meekness, Simplicity and Courage. And 'tis a surprising Change to find such a sudden and extraordinary Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in so many of her Sons; and those otherwise, both her Ornament and Glory. This turns her Joy into Sadness, and her rejoycing into Tears. Her Clergy for their Learning and Piety, and Constancy in the Faith, used to be the <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the VVorld.</hi> And how fearful, how sollicitously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd is she, (lest for Reasons of another nature, and which she is unwilling to mention) it be now said—<hi>Stupor mundi Clerus Brittannus?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:35"/>
            <head>Post-script TO THE AUTHOR.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have thought fit not to give your Bookseller the trouble of these Papers. And one Reason is, because as (I remember) it was about four Months before I heard any thing of that short Answer, which (according to your Direction) I before sent to Mr. <hi>Randal Taylor:</hi> So that I had almost given over all expectations of seeing any thing against it. But at last, when you had finished the great Work, you were resolv'd, That the World should know it by giving notice of your Performance, in the Public <hi>Gazette.</hi> And truely, had you not done so, it's probable, that I (as well as others) had still been ignorant, That any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn was made.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:35"/>
            <p>As soon as I had thus found, that you had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken me, I expected that your Atcheivement had been answerable to the pompous Proclamation of it; And therefore I presently sent for your Book. But how fearful, may you imagin, was I to open it, and see my self led in Triumph after your <hi>Victorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions!</hi> However, I ventur'd to read it from one end to the other; And after I had done, found my self as safe and sound, as I was before, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the terrible Shocks, of your <hi>High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Assertions.</hi> This encourag'd me to set Pen to Paper, and defend what I had Written: To defend one's self is natural, but the obligation to defend the truth is indispensible. And truely, the Cause is so good, and your Objections so very insignificant, That no Commendation is due to me, if these things, which I offer to the ingenuous and honest Reader, shall be thought a full and sufficient Reply to all your pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cavils, false Reasonings, ungrammatical Periods, and (what is worse than all these) malicious Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon a Company of Men, whose Learning and Piety, will perpetuate their Names, as long as useful Knowledge and true Christianity shall have any esteem amongst Men.</p>
            <p>Let me farther acquaint you, that if you shall ask, why this Answer comes out so late; it is for a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, which you know very well, and I need not stand
<pb facs="tcp:97880:36"/> to explain. Had the Press been as open for Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of this kind, as it is for those of a contrary nature; My Papers had been Printed, as they were finished, within a very little time, after I received your Answer. However at last you see, they have made a shift to get into the World. And as for the Principles, which they maintain, they are free <hi>Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons,</hi> and naturalized Subjects of <hi>England;</hi> And how much soever they may be blamed, yet if they may be heard (as the Judges of the <hi>Areopagus</hi> did their Advocates) in the dark, they are not afraid to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Bar of the strictest Justice. That is, if Partialities of Affection and Passion be laid aside, they will I perswade my self not only be acquitted, but encourag'd—But as for Men of your interests and prejudices, they expects nothing less than to be put out of the Protection of the Laws; and (as Strangers and Foreigners) sent back to the <hi>poor, distressed and suffering State of Christianity,</hi> from which (you confess) they came, and to which (as you will have it) they only belong. In the mean time, how hardly soever they may be treated by you and your Brethren, they assure themselves of a kind Reception from all, whose Prayers and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are sincerely directed to the good and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the State and Church of <hi>England;</hi> and more especially (when by such Judges as your self,
<pb facs="tcp:97880:36"/> they shall be condemn'd as <hi>pernicious and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Principles</hi>) they doubt not but that, at least, they shall have the <hi>benefit of their Clrgy;</hi> for whose Reputation and Honour they are chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97880:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>